<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The devout companion: containing prayers and meditations for every day in the week: and for several occasions, ordinary and extraordinary.</title>
            <author>E. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2450A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213357</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012647</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174612</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05787)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174612)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2692:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The devout companion: containing prayers and meditations for every day in the week: and for several occasions, ordinary and extraordinary.</title>
                  <author>E. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The twelfth edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>188, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Henry Rhodes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed E. S., p. 6.</note>
                  <note>Contents: p. [1]-[4].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with some loss of text. T.p. stained with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174612:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Devout Companion:</hi> Containing PRAYERS AND <hi>MEDITATIONS</hi> FOR <hi>Every Day in the Week:</hi> AND FOR Several Occaſions. <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 55. 17.</bibl> Evening and Morning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and at Noon will I pray, and cry aloud, and he ſhall hear my Voice.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Twelfth Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Henry Rhodes,</hi>
               </hi> at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>he corner of <hi>Brile-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:174612:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174612:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Truly Honoured, The LADY <hi>J. C.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AT Your Requeſt theſe enſuing <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Meditations</hi> were compoſed, which I here preſent to Your view; not that You want my weak Inſtructions, for You are known to be ſo good a Proficient in God's School, and have more of this Heavenly Language by Heart, than I can inſtruct you by Precept.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Meditations</hi> I have taken from the Pſalms of that ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Royal Prophet; and this Key opens not only the Kingdom of Grace, but the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven too; it being an exact Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all Chriſtian Vertues.</p>
            <p>No Worſhipping can be more true or more ſpiritual than the <hi>Pſalter,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:174612:3"/> ſaid with a pure Mind and a hearty Devotion. For <hi>David</hi> was God's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to the Church, teaching and admoniſhing (as our Duty is to each other) in Pſalms and Hymns and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Songs, making melody to the Lord.</p>
            <p>In your Voyage to the Almighty, You might have (I doubt not) a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Card or Compaſs to ſail by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than this Form of Prayer which I preſcribe; yet I beſeech You encourage others by Your pious Example to feed upon this Milk for Babes, (thoſe which are weak) by taſting of it your Self.</p>
            <p>So recommending it to Your Pious Acceptation, wiſhing You all Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that this Earthly Paradiſe can afford, whiſt You remain upon Earth, and at the laſt a Crown of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Glory in the higheſt Heavens, is the earnest deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam, </salute> 
               <signed>Your humble and faithful Servant in Chriſt Jeſus, E. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:174612:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Devout Companion:</hi> Containing <hi>MEDITATIONS</hi> AND PRAYERS, For every Day in the Week, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Preparatory Prayer againſt wandring Thoughts, and vain Imaginations.</head>
               <q>
                  <p>Thrice Holy, Bleſſed and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trinity, Three Perſons and One God, have mercy upon me a miſerable Sinner.</p>
               </q>
               <p>O Almighty God, the only Giver and Beſtower of all good things, and without whoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174612:4"/> ſpecial Favour and Grace, no Man hath Power to perform any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Duty as he ought to do: O Lord! I know not what to pray for as I ought, O let thy Spirit help my Infirmities, and enable me to offer up a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sacrifice, acceptable to thee by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Make me to remember into whoſe Preſence I am come, and with whom I have to do; even with a God of infin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te Majeſty; before whom the Cherubims veil their Faces, as being aſtoniſhed at the Preſence of ſo great a God as thou art. How dare I then, a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t vile and ſinful Creature, who am but Duſt and Aſhes, preſume to appear at this time before thee, who have drunk Iniquity like Water, breaking ſo often thy holy Laws and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174612:4"/> by committing thoſe things thou forbiddeſt: and leaving undone thoſe good things thou commandeſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>But I come unto thee, O Lord, in the name of thy dear Son, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous; who hath redeemed me with his moſt precious Blood. O then look upon me in him, and for the merits of his Sufferings, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all my Sins, and blot out my Offences. Strike an awful reverence in my Soul, that I may continually keep a watch over my Thoughts, Words, and Actions, leaſt my Preſumption, and want of due Reverence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Deity, ſhould turn my Prayers into Sin.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Give me a lively apprehenſion of all my wants and neceſſities,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174612:5"/> and a right Underſtanding both of thoſe Bleſſings which I have received from thee, and of thoſe great Mercies which thou haſt promiſed to beſtow on them that ask thee; that ſo I may be endued with Expreſſions both for Prayer and Thankfulneſs; and may become able, by the aſſiſtance of thy Grace, to pour out my Soul continually before thee. Support me with Faith, that I may come with a good aſſurance to thy Throne of Grace, to offer up my earneſt Supplications unto thee, and let me not go away from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence without a Bleſſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Grant, Lord, that this holy Exerciſe of Prayer may prove a delight to me! O make me conſtant and diligent in the uſe of it; remembring the ſpeedy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174612:5"/> acceſs the Prayers of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful have in thy Preſence; and what a great Privilege it is for poor Mortals to unfold their Wants, and lay open their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Griefs before thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Ever, O Lord, let the end of my Prayers be to thy Glory; always exerciſing a Conſcience void of Offence, by offering up my Thankſgivings for Mercies received, as I ſhall be earneſt in ſuing for thoſe Gifts and Graces I ſtand in need of. Grant this, O heavenly Father, for the ſake of thy dear Son, my only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Redeemer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>Meditations for <hi>Sunday.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is the Day which the Lord hath made, a Day of Reſt to our Bodies, and for the Benefit of our Souls. O let us rejoice, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174612:6"/> be glad in it all the Days of our L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; leaving off our worldly Thoughts and Employments, and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeking after our future Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Great i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lord, and great is the Honour of this day above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The <hi>Jews</hi> kept Holy the Seventh Day, and we Chriſtians the <hi>Sunday,</hi> or Lord's Day: They in their Sabbath were eſpecially to remember the Creation of the World, but we in ours, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt, who hath made a way for us into that better wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d which we expect hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>This convinceth the Folly of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who are ſo ſuperſtitious in obſerving the Ceremony of Reſt, as that they think they ought not to prepare any Food for their bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſtenance on the Sabbath-Day; neither do any work, tho' it be for the Reſection of Life it ſelf.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174612:6"/> But God in the Inſtitution of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bbath ſo reſted, whoſe Example we ought to imitate, as that he ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſting from <hi>doing good,</hi> but in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſing to Create, he continued to Preſerve, of which our Saviour ſaith, <hi>My Father work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hitherto, and I work.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>This Day is ſet apart, to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; Firſt more ſolemnly and publickly in the Houſe of God, from whence none ought to abſent himſelf, unleſs ſickneſs or ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary occaſion prevent him. Secondly, at home privately pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with your Family, or in your Cloſet, exerciſing thoſe other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Reading and Meditation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>O Praiſe the Lord then, O my Soul, and enter into Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with thy ſelf upon all his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Conſider what a great Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit it is to thee, that there is ſuch a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174612:7"/> ſet time weekly for thy ſpiritual Relief and Comfort; caſt off all worldly Buſineſs then, and freely embrace this joyful Day of harveſt whereby we may lay up in ſtore for the whole Week, nay even for our whole Lives.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>This day furniſhes us with that Golden Rule, by which we may ſquare all our Actions, and at laſt attain to the perfection of him whom the Royal Pſalmiſt makes mention of, to be a pattern of true Goodneſs, and tells you, The Lord ordereth a good Man's going, and maketh his way acceptable to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: Though he fall, he ſhall not be caſt away; for the Lord up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth him with his Hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>The Law of God is in his Heart and his goings ſhall not ſlide. O ſend out thy Light and thy Truth, that they may lead me and bring me unto thy holy Hill, and to thy
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174612:7"/> Dwelling. And that I may go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Altar of God, even unto the God of my Joy and Gladneſs, and upon the Harp will I give Thanks unto thee, O God my God. We wait for thy Loving-kindneſs, O God, in the midſt of thy Temple.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Morning Prayer for <hi>Sunday:</hi> For the Worſhip of God.</head>
               <p>MOſt mighty and gracious God, which haſt brought me out of the Night's Darkneſs into the marvellous Light of thy Truth, to ſee the Light of thy Love, that I may rejoice in the Day of my Viſitation and Salvation, whereby the Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring from on high hath viſited me, and in the Day of Salvation thou wilt ſuccour me.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>This Day make me hear thy Voice, and not harden my Heart
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174612:8"/> through unbelief or deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sin, but that by Faith I may enter into thy promiſed Reſt: Give Grace unto me, O Lord, and to all People, to walk circumſpectly and diligently, to do ſuch good Works wherewith thou may'ſt be well pleaſed; ſo that walking in thy Ways, and according to thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I may work out my own Salvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling; that as my Body draws nearer the Grave, my Soul may approach the nearer Heaven.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee, to be merciful unto me, and as of thy goodneſs thou giveſt me time to Repent, ſo of thine infinite Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy give me ſuch a true, holy, and perfect Repentance, never to be repented of: And grant, O Lord, that I may unfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174612:8"/> Reſolve and effectually La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to amend my Life this Day, even to my Life's end, that ſo I may never be tempted above what I am able to bear.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>I am beginning the Week, but alas I begin not to be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in my Life and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the more Weeks paſs over my Head, the greater bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of Sin I take upon my Back, and do the more defile my Conſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. Day by Day I run on in my Wickedneſs, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſay to my ſelf, What have I done? If I ſhould at this Week's end caſt up the Account of my good Deeds, how few Lines, alas would they contain!</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and forgive me all my Sins, remove them out of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174612:9"/> as far diſtant as the Eaſt is from the Weſt. Accept of me in the Death and Paſſion of thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, that wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I ſhall come into thy Temple, to compaſs thine Altar, my Prayers may come up before thee as Incenſe, and the lifting up of my Hands as an Evening Sacrifice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>And as I deſire that thou wouldſt hear me calling upon thee in my Prayers, ſo give me Grace to hear thee calling upon me in thy Word. It is the word of Truth, Wiſdom, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Reconciliation, which is able to ſave my Soul in the Day of the Lord Jeſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> grant therefore that I may hear it with Reverence, receive it with Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and mingle it with Faith, that it may accompliſh in me
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174612:9"/> that good Work, for which thou haſt ſent it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>I know not alas how to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thee as I ought; my Sins have made a Wall of ſeparation betwixt-thee and me, ſo that neither my Prayers can aſcend up unto thee as they ſhould, nor thy Graces deſcend upon me as I would deſire them. O break, I beſeech thee, this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-Wall, ſlide thou down into the ſecret Habitation of my Heart by thy mighty Power, and ſtrengthen every privy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of that neglected Houſe, by the brightneſs of thy Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; feed thou every ſecret part both of my Mind and Body; keep me from Sin, and let me ſerve thee this Day in thy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:174612:10"/>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs thoſe Meſſengers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thine, O Lord, that break unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me the Bread of Life. As tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haſt placed them like Beacons o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy holy Hill, the Church, giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them Grace (with the five Wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Virgins) that their Light may never go forth, but ſtill ſhine brightly to arm us thy People againſt the Invaſion of that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of Mankind, the Devil, and his Army, that Day and Night ſeek to devour us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="part">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>Let me ſpend the reſt of my uncertain Life in a renewed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for my Sins paſt, and an holy Reſolution to ſerve thee for the time to come. Grant, O Lord, theſe and all other Graces meet for me, for thy Son's ſake, my only Lord and Saviour; To whom with Thee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174612:10"/> and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Praiſe and Glory, for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer at our Entrance into the Church.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, who dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in that Light which no mortal is able to approach unto, yet art preſent with us in this thy ſacred Houſe! O Lord, my God, my only Comfort and Riches, what am I that I dare ſpeak unto thee? I am thy poor Servant, teach me to climb and aſcend up unto thee by Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Prayer.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Make this Religious Place as thine Ark, and let thy Dove, thy holy Spirit, enter in at theſe windows; let a good meaſure of thy word, and an effectual
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174612:11"/> preaching thereof, be evermore preſerved and diſtributed in this place; let no evil Leproſie ever enter into theſe Walls, nor the hand of Sacrilege ever fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>The Harveſt is great, but the Labourers are few; ſend forth, I beſeech thee, more into thy Vineyard, and endue them with ſuch Wiſdom as becometh thy holy Goſpel. Open unto them the Door of Utterance, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me the Gate of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they may faithfully diſpend thy Myſteries, and I fervently embrace the ſame, to thy Glory, and the Salvation of my Soul, through Jeſus Chriſt my only Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:174612:11"/>
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Sunday</hi> Noon: For Perſeverance.</head>
               <p>O God, moſt gracious and merciful, who hateſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing that thou haſt made, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt willing that all ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake of thy Coeleſtial Love; I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave this day viſited thy Houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Place where thine Honour dwelleth; grant, I beſeech thee, that I may ſtill perſevere and preſs forward in that holy Duty of ſerving thee all the Days of my Life.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Vouchſafe to me, O Lord, I beſeech thee, thy Heavenly Grace, that I may avoid the precipices of Sin, which lead to deſtruction, and endeavour to ſerve thee, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the Days of my Life: Grant that in thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174612:12"/> Light I may ſee Light; and as I have begun this Day in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and lauding thy holy Name ſo let it end to thy Glory: To whom be aſcribed all Honour, Power, and Glory, both now and for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Afternoon, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sermon. A Thanksgiving for the Word preached.</head>
               <p>O Lord moſt Holy, whoſe Truth endureth from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting to everlaſting; Thou haſt been merciful and gracious to me, and haſt filled me which am hungry with good things, and none of thy Servants doſt thou ſend empty away from thy holy Sanctuary: Plant thy Fear in my Heart, give me Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and good Underſtanding, and make me to have pleaſure
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174612:12"/> in thee and all thy works; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>beying the Precepts of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Goſpel, and performing the Conditions of thy Covenant which thou haſt eſtabliſhed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver in Truth and Equity, in Verity and Judgment, I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orthily praiſe and adore thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly Name among the Faithful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Life, and in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of Saints in the Life to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome, through thy Mercies, O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſſed Jeſu, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Honour and Glory, now and or ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Sunday</hi> Evening: For Pardon of Sin.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſs thoſe many weakneſſes and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ections I am guilty of, in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174612:13"/> my performance of the Duti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this Day: I have called up on thee for the pardon and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giveneſs of my Sins: I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heard thy holy Word, but y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> find my ſelf a very unprofit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble Servant. So that, O Lord though I have done thy Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I have done it ſo negligently that I may rather expect th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fire of thy Anger, than a Ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing from thee.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>But if thou, O God, ſhould be extream to mark what done amiſs, O Lord, who ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> abide it: or ſtand before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> when thou art angry? Remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber that I am but duſt and aſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and the work of thine ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hands: Pardon, I beſeech the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and paſs by all my Sins, Negl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gences, and Ignorances; loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not upon the weakneſs of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:174612:13"/> Fleſh, but upon the willingneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f my Spirit, and ſo cover all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y imperfections, with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erfect and abſolute obedience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f thy dear Son, that thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rifices offered up by me this day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay be by thee accepted, in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd for that Sacrifice which Chriſt Jeſus offered upon the Croſs once for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>And as I earneſtly deſire that my Sacrifices may be pleaſing and acceptable to thee, ſo let thine Ordinances be profitable to me. And as thou haſt this day ſown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n my heart the precious ſeed of thy Word, ſo let neither the Fowls of the Air devour it, nor the Cares of the World choak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it; but let the former and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atter Rain of thy bleſſing come often upon it, that it may bring forth in me the Fruits of true
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174612:14"/> Repentance, and hearty amen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Life. Pardon my m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifold Sins by which I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> provoked thee this very day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Be thou unto me a mercifu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, in deſpite of the Snare and Deluſions which Sin lays i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the way for my Deſtruction and keep me under the ſhadow of thy Wings, in perpetua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Peace and Safety. Bleſs me thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Night; ſleeping or waking, giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thine Angels charge over me that at whatſoever hour thou calleſt me, I may, like a faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful Soldier, ſtand ready prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to encounter Death, and to follow the Lamb whereſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever he goeth. Grant theſe things, O bleſſed Father, for thy Son Jeſus Chriſt his ſake my only Saviour and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:174612:14"/>
               <head>Meditations for <hi>Monday:</hi> Out of the Pſalms: For a holy Life.</head>
               <p>MY ſong ſhall be of mercy and judgment, unto thee, O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord, will I ſing. Let me have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſtanding in the way of godlineſs.</p>
               <p>When wilt thou come unto me? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will walk i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my houſe with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect heart. I will take no wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing: I hate the Sins of unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulneſs: there ſhall no ſuch cleave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto me.</p>
               <p>A froward heart ſhall depart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom me; I will not know a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Perſon.</p>
               <p>Whoſo privily ſlandereth his neighbour, him will I deſtroy.</p>
               <p>Whoſo hath alſo a proud look and high ſtomach, I will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him.</p>
               <p>There ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll no deceitful perſon dwell in my houſe, he that telleth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yes ſhall not tarry in my ſight.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on deſtroy all the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174612:15"/> that are in the Land: that may root out all wicked doe from the City of the Lord.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Monday</hi> Morning For a Holy Life.</head>
               <p>O God moſt Holy and Righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous, who ſheweſt Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy unto thouſands, and hateſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing thy own hands hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made: who filleſt me with thy loving kindneſs every Morning and keepeſt me in Peace and Safety in the Night ſeaſon.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>I confeſs, O Lord, that I am altogether Vanity, a ſhadow of Death, a dark Dungeon, a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and empty Ground, where no Water is, but deluges of Wrath and Confuſion: But, O Lord, I abhor my ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174612:15"/> before thee in duſt and aſhes; and as Sins of Infirmity have thrown me down, raiſe me up again, I beſeech thee, by the Gift of Penitence, that I may lead a holy Life with all Humility, Truth and Juſtice, Godlineſs and Honeſty, in this preſent World.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>I bleſs thy holy Name for thy Care and Protection over me this Night; that thou haſt ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought me to the beginning of this day, delivering me from the ſhadow of Death O Lord continue thy wonted goodneſs towards me this Day, and grant that all my Prayers, Words, Works and Actions, may begin and end in thy Glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Keep me, O Lord, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, this day without,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174612:16"/> ſin, and ſo repleniſh me with thy Favour and Grace that my heart may rejoyce and delight in thy praiſes. Deliver me, O Lord, from lying Lips, and from a deceitful Tongue; keep me from the Snare of the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and from the noiſom and infectious Peſtilence; from deadly Vexation, mortal Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſudden Death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Protect me in the day of my Trouble; give me a contented Mind, which may remain unto me a continual Feaſt, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever changes or chances may befall me in this tranſitory Life. Grant that I may yield up my ſelf to thy good Pleaſure in all things, and be obedient un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe holy Commandments which thou haſt appointed for my Rule and Guide. So that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174612:16"/> at the laſt I may find, that in keeping thy Holy Laws there is great Reward: Grant this, O heavenly Father, for thy Son's ſake, my only Redeemer.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Monday</hi> Noon: For Forgiveneſs of Sins.</head>
               <p>O God the ſearcher of all hearts, and from whom no ſecrets are hid, but are laid open to thine all-ſeeing Eye; I here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my Sins unto thee, and mine Iniquities, which are many in number: I come unto thee, O Lord, who art the fountain of all goodneſs, and forgiveſt all thoſe that with hearty Repentance come unto thee: Pardon and remit all thoſe Sins, which this day I have committed againſt thy Divine Majeſty. Purge me with Hyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174612:17"/> and I ſhall be clean; waſh me, and I ſhall be whiter than Snow: Let the dew of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and the fire of thy Love, blot out all my Sins and purifie my Soul.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Create in me a clean Heart, and renew a right Spirit within me: Let me not be for ever ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the ſweet refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of thy Favourand preſence; but give me the comfort of thy help again, and let thy free Spirit looſe me from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Sin, and eſtabliſh me in the freedom and liberty of the Sons of God: So ſhall I praiſe thy Name, and evermore ſing of thy Righteouſneſs in the Congregation of thy redeemed ones, now, henceforth, and for ever.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:174612:17"/>
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Monday</hi> Night: For Preſervation.</head>
               <p>O Lord moſt Holy, I praiſe and magnifie thy holy Name for preſerving of me this Day both in Soul and Body. O thou who art <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega,</hi> bleſs and defend me with thy heavenly Grace this Night: let my reſt be in thee, and grant that neither much ſleep overwhelm me, nor Satan in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade me: though my Eyes ſleep, yet, O Lord, keep my Heart waking; leſt the ſubtle Tempter overtake me, and I ſleep in perpetual ſilence. Keep me in the arms of thy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; give ſleep to my Eyes and ſlumber unto my Eye-lids; compaſs me about, and raiſe me up again to the joyful ſight
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174612:18"/> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ext Morning Light; and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter this miſerable Life is ended, grant that in thy Light I may ſee Light for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>Meditations for <hi>Tueſday:</hi> For defence of our Innocenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and againſt the malice of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</head>
               <p>O Lord, my God in thee have I put my truſt: Save me from all them that perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cute me, and deliver me.</p>
               <p>Leſt he devour my Soul like a Lion; and tear it in pieces, while there is none to help.</p>
               <p>O Lord my God, if I have done any ſuch thing, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f there be any wickedneſs in my hands;</p>
               <p>If I have rewarded evil unto him that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> friendly with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea I have delivered him that without any cauſe is mine Enemy:</p>
               <p>Then let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Enemy perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cute
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174612:18"/> my S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and take me: Yea, let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead my life down upon the Earth, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y mine honour in the duſt</p>
               <p>Stand up, O Lord, in thy wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, and lift up thy ſelf; becauſe of the indignation of mine Enemies, ariſe up f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r me in the judgment that thou haſt commanded.</p>
               <p>And ſo ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Congregation of the people come about thee: For their ſakes therefore lift up thy ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> again.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſhall judge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Give ſentence with me, O Lord, according to my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and accord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is in me.</p>
               <p>O let the wickedneſs of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly come to an end; but guide thou the juſt.</p>
               <p>For the righteous God trieth the very heart and reins.</p>
               <p>My Help cometh of God, which preſerveth them that are true of heart.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:174612:19"/>
               <p>God is a righteous Judge, ſtrong and patient; and God is provoked every day.</p>
               <p>If a man will not turn, he will whet his ſword; he hath bent his bow, and made it ready.</p>
               <p>He hath prepared for him the inſtruments of death: he ordained his arrows againſt the perſecutors.</p>
               <p>Behold he travaileth with miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief: he hath conceived ſorrow and brought forth ungodlineſs.</p>
               <p>He hath graven and digged up a pit, and is fallen himſelf into the deſtruction that he made for others.</p>
               <p>For his travail ſhall come upon his own head; and his wickedneſs ſhall fall upon his own pate.</p>
               <p>I will give thanks unto the Lord according to his righteouſneſs, and will praiſe the Name of the Lord the moſt High.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:174612:19"/>
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Tueſday</hi> Morning: For Protection from our Enemies.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, who art a ſtrong rock of defence to all thoſe who truſt in thee; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me, I beſeech thee, from thoſe Mouths, who, like Lions roaring for their Prey, ſeek to devour me: Abate their Pride, aſſwage their Malice, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found their Devices; ſave me from the hands of all thoſe who ſeek to do me evil, and let their wickedneſs and Helliſh contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance come utterly to an end for evermore.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>I magnifie thy holy Name for thy preſervation of me this Night. Grant that I may walk this Day according to thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly will in all things, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:174612:20"/> evil for good, but on the contrary good for evil. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe from me all clouds of Envy, Hatred or Malice which ſeem to hover over me; and though heavineſs may endure for a Night; yet, O Lord, let thy Joy, and light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance appear in the Morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Give me Grace not to rejoice in any thing that diſpleaſeth thee, but evermore to delight in thoſe things which are moſt pleaſing to thee, be they never ſo diſagreeable to my deſires. Defend me, O Lord, from all ſhame and diſgraces of this life; mortifie all the corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are in me, and pardon the innumerable Sins which I have committed. Bleſs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and keep me this Day by thy power from ſin, ſhame and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:174612:20"/> all evil, and ſo direct me by thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace, that all my thoughts, words and works may pleaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hee, through the merits of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, my only Lord and Saviour.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Tueſday</hi> Noon: For God's Grace and Favour.</head>
               <p>O God moſt Holy, who guideſt and governeſt all thoſe that truſt in thee; I beſeech thee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me daily; cheriſh, comfort, govern, and counſel me in all my enterpriſes, ſo that I may employ this Day, and all the days of my Life, according to thy bleſſed will; ſetting thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways before my eyes, and aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at thy Glory.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Let me earneſtly ſeek, and find thee, O my hearts deſire; and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:174612:21"/> let me hold thee faſt, whom my Soul loveth; let me enjoy thee, O my ſpiritual comfort, in all my faculties, even in my heart let me poſſeſs thee. Be thou for ever preſent with me in all my undertakings; let thy Favour refreſh me, and thy Grace which is ſufficient for me, ſupport me; though I walk through this valley and ſhadow of Death, I may fear no Evil while thy rod and thy ſtaff comfort me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Convert and turn the hearts of thoſe which ſeek to do me E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; and do hate me without a cauſe: keep me from their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which is fierce, and from the wrath of them which are cruel; and bring them down in their high imaginations, leſt they be too proud. Grant that the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:174612:21"/> remaining part of this Day, I may walk in thy Fear; ſo that at the laſt I may enter into thy Glory, through the merits of Jeſus Chriſt my only Saviour.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Tueſday</hi> Night: Of Thanksgiving for God's Mercies.</head>
               <p>I Render thee moſt humble and hearty Thanks for thy Preſervation of me this Day, and relieving me according to my ſeveral Neceſſities. Thou haſt this Day paſt defended me from all Danger, given me my daily Bread, and hourly breath: continue ſtill, I beſeech thee, thy undeſerved Mercies towards me; and accept this my Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:174612:22"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Let not the meanneſs of my Devotion cauſe thee to turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thine Eyes from me, but according to thine accuſtomed kindneſs, ſpare thy Servant, good Lord, and be not angry with him for ever. Preſerve me this Night, O thou that preſerveſt all the World; and taking my natural repoſe, I may through thy protection and ready help, be defended both now and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>Meditations for <hi>Wedneſday.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Heavens declare the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſheweth his handy-work.</p>
               <p>One day telleth another; and one night certifieth another.</p>
               <p>There is neither ſpeech nor lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; but their voices are heard among them.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:174612:22"/>
               <p>Their ſound is gone out into all lands; and their words unto the ends of the world.</p>
               <p>In them hath he ſet a Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle for the Sun; which cometh forth as a Bridegroom out of his Chamber, and rejoiceth as a giant to run his courſe.</p>
               <p>It goeth forth from the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part of the Heaven, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth about unto the end of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and there is nothing hid from the heat thereof.</p>
               <p>The Law of the Lord is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled Law, converting the Soul; the Teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, and giveth wiſdom unto the ſimple.</p>
               <p>The Statutes of the Lord are right, and rejoice the heart; the Commandment of the Lord is pure, and giveth light unto the Eyes.</p>
               <p>The fear of the Lord is clean, and endureth for ever: the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.</p>
               <p>More to be deſired are they than
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:174612:23"/> gold; yea, than much fine gold; ſweeter alſo than honey, and the honey-comb.</p>
               <p>Moreover, by them is thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant taught: and in keeping of them there is great reward.</p>
               <p>Who can tell how oft he offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth? O cleanſe thou me from my ſecret faults.</p>
               <p>Keep thy ſervant alſo from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſins, leſt they get the dominion over me: ſo ſhall I be undefiled and innocent from the great offence.</p>
               <p>Let the words of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart be always acceptable in thy ſight,</p>
               <p>O Lord my ſtrength and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:174612:23"/>
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Wedneſday</hi> Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; For Repentance.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, before whom all Creatures both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth do bow, fear and tremble; I a moſt wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and miſerable Creature, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected with the weighty burthen of my Sins, fly unto thee for Succour. Plant in my heart the Fear of thy Name, and in my body the purity and cleanneſs of Charity; and let them abide there for ever. Cleanſe me from all my ſecret Sins, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me from preſumptuous and great Offences: Touch my heart, O God, with true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that thy Judgments preſent and imminent, may be prevented and removed; and the overflowing ſilver ſtream and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:174612:24"/> current of thy Mercies, be never at an end.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Be gracious to my Relations in the fleſh, my Friends in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with all thoſe to whom I am any way bounden, or deſire to be commended unto thee in my Prayers and Supplications. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, O Lord, and caſt out of my heart all evil Imagination, Hatred, Malice, and all Uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſs, and whatſoever is contrary to thy holy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>I praiſe thy holy Name for thy preſervation of me this Night paſt, for the Gifts and Graces of thy Bleſſed Spirit; as Faith in thy Promiſes, Hope of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Life when this is ended, and ſtrength againſt all the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Satan; all which have
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:174612:24"/> proceeded from the Fountain of thy Mercy: As thou haſt of thy Providence kept me ever ſince I was born, and in Mercy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved me the beginning of this Week, ſo to my Comfort grant me the continuance of the ſame, through Jeſus Chriſt, my only Redeemer and Advocate.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Wedneſday</hi> Noon: For God's particular Care of us.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, I cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for Mercy, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon my Sins cry againſt me for Juſtice; all the day long will I lift up my Heart unto thee: ſhut not thine Ear, O Lord, but hear my complaint, and that right ſoon. Let me in all things ſee that I am upheld by thee: Let me perceive it is thy Work, by the Health of my
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:174612:25"/> Body and Peace of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the Gift of my Mind, the Credit of my Name, and the Work of my Calling.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>But, alas, can there be greater Mercies, O Lord, than thou haſt already expreſſed towards me! for whilſt I have enjoyed all thy Mercies, others have lived in penury and want, in ignorance, profaneneſs, and without thee in the World.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>What can I render unto the Lord for all his Mercies towards me? Let me not pledge <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Botler in his Cup of Oblivion, but <hi>David</hi> rather in his Cup of Salvation; and if my ſingle heart be too barren of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, let me borrow a <hi>magnificat</hi> O my Soul, to magnifie Thee O Lord, and let my Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:174612:25"/> in thee, O God my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. What ſhall I ſay unto thee, O thou Redeemer of all Mankind? I will praiſe thy holy Name. For evermore inſpire me with thy Spirit, convert me from Evil, confirm me in all Goodneſs, and bring me at laſt unto thy heavenly Kingdom.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Wedneſday</hi> Night: For deliverance from Sin.</head>
               <p>MOST merciful God, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to open the Eyes of my underſtanding, that I may come to a particular knowledge of my ſecret Sins, eſpecially thoſe I am moſt incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to. Soften my hard and flinty heart, that I may ſigh and groan under t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> weight of my moſt preſſing ſins; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:174612:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:174612:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:174612:27"/> them a Burthen too heavy for me to bear.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Stir up in me all dull and dead Affections, that I may hunger and thirſt after thee, the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of Life. Forgive me all my miſdemeanours of this day paſt; make me to remember, that Sin is filthy and loathſome, even in the greateſt pleaſure and act thereof; teach me to keep a continual watch over my inward and outward Man, whereby I may be afraid to commit the leaſt Sin, that ſo I may walk according to thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will in all things.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Give me this Night ſweet and comfortable reſt, and fit me, O Lord, for the duties and ſervice of the next day: Turn from me O Lord thoſe judgments which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:174612:27"/> my ſins have juſtly deſerved, and renew thoſe hopes which thou haſt been pleaſed to fruſtrate; crown me with thoſe bleſſings, which thou haſt promiſed to all theſe that fear thy Name, ſo that at the laſt I may attain everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Happineſs, and live with thee in perpetual peace and ſafety for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>Meditations for <hi>Thurſday.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Sing unto the Lord a new ſong; for he hath done marvellous things. With his own right hand, and with his holy arm hath he gotten himſelf the victory.</p>
               <p>The Lord declared his Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: his R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghteouſneſs hath he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſhewed in the ſight of the Heathen.</p>
               <p>He hath remembred his Mercy and Truth towards the Houſe of Iſrael; and all the ends of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:174612:28"/> world have ſeen the ſalvation of our God.</p>
               <p>Shew your ſelves joyful unto the Lord, all ye lands; ſing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, and give thanks.</p>
               <p>Praiſe the Lord upon the harp: ſing to the harp with a Pſalm of Thankſgiving.</p>
               <p>With trumpets alſo and ſhawms: O ſhew your ſelves joyful before the Lord the King.</p>
               <p>Let the Sea make a noiſe, and all that therein is; the round world, and they that dwell therein.</p>
               <p>Let the floods clap their hands, and let the hills be joyful together before the Lord; for he is come to judge the earth.</p>
               <p>With righteouſneſs ſhall he judge the world, and the people with equity.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:174612:28"/>
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Thurſday</hi> Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. A Sacrifice of Praiſe.</head>
               <p>O Moſt glorious and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lord God who with thy holy arm hath gotten for me the Victory over Sin, Hell, and the Grave. I praiſe thee, O Lord, from the very bottom of my heart, for all thy love and boundleſs mercy and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for thy holy Incarnation, Paſſion, Reſurrection and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention into Heaven, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the right hand of God the Father; where thou makeſt Interceſſion for me.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>In thy merits I beſeech thee to look upon me: thou art that living Sacrifice that was offered up for me, and in thy Name do I offer up unto thee this my
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:174612:29"/> morning Sacrifice; evermore praiſing thee, and magnifying thy holy Name. Mortifie in me all fleſhly Corruptions; quicken me in the inner Man: By the power of thy death let me die unto Sin, and by the power of thy Reſurrection, let me riſe to Righteouſneſs and newneſs of Life. Let the one as an antidote expel the poiſon of Ungodlyneſs, and the other as a reſtorative excite me to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Enlighten my Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that I may know thy Will; reform my Life, that I may do all things aright, and to diſcern Good and Evil. Teach me to fear thy Name, to neglect all things in regard of thee, to be grieved at my own and others Sins; but rejoyce exceedingly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:174612:29"/> whenſoever I can pleaſe thee. Let me this Day labour, that whatſoever I do may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in thy ſight; as I am thy Servant, let me depend upon thee, and as I am a Chriſtian, walk worthy of my Vocation and Calling.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Be gracious and favourable unto the whole Church, and bleſs every particular Member thereof; be good to the light of our Eyes, the breath of our Noſtrils, thy <hi>Solomon,</hi> our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King; bleſs thine own Tribe, the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> the Nobility, Gentry, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, and let thy Peace reſt upon thoſe that pray for our Peace, whereſoever diſperſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Face of the whole Earth. Lord keep me the remaining part of this Day in thy Truth,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:174612:30"/> and give me Peace and true Faith in thee, now and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Thurſday</hi> Noon: For God's Bleſſing on our Endeavours.</head>
               <p>O Eternal and moſt gracious God, who though thou art ever infinite, yet enlargeſt thy ſelf by the number of our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and takeſt our often Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to thee to be an addition to thy Glory; ſo great is thy Humility toward poor Mortals. I moſt humbly beſeech thee, O Lord, that thine Eyes may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually attend upon me, and thy Grace daily defend me from all danger: ſuccour, cheriſh, and comfort me in my Neceſſities, and govern all my counſels, Studies, and Labours, ſo that I
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:174612:30"/> may ſpend this Day according to thy bleſſed Will, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my own Conſcience; that warily avoiding all things, that may diſpleaſe thee, and ſetting always before my Eyes thy Fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I may by the aſſiſtance of thy heavenly Grace, and the guidance of thy holy Spirit, work that which is acceptable and pleaſing unto thee, unto thy Praiſe and Glory, for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Thurſday</hi> Night: For Deliverance from Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Death.</head>
               <p>O Lord moſt holy, the giver of all good things, and the protector of all thoſe that love thee, I give thee moſt humble and hearty thanks, nor only for thy preſervation of me this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:174612:31"/> day, but all my life; O Lord forgive me the Offences I have committed againſt thee this Day, blot out all my ſins with the blood of thy dear Son <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſus Chriſt, and I beſeech thee for his ſake remember them no more.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Vouchſafe, O Lord, to extend thine accuſtomed goodneſs, and protection over me this Night, that I may peaceably and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take my reſt, which thou haſt appointed for the refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my wearied and weak body: and I beſeech thee to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me, that nothing hurt me; keep me alſo, good Lord, from ſudden and unprovided Death, and preſerve me by the guard of thy holy Angels, that I may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy my reſt this Night in thee until the Morning, and then give
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:174612:31"/> my ſelf to the fulfilling of my Duty, the diſcharge of my Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and the working of thy will unto my life's end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>In whoſe Name I referr my ſelf wholly to the Almighty Protection, even in the Name of thy bleſſed Son Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous; beſeeching thee that when this Life ſhall have an end, and my laſt ſleep being come, I may take my everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſt with thee in thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom; for the which Kingdom, I do heartily beſeech thee of thine ineſtimable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to fit and prepare me and all other thy Servants to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of the ſame; for the glory of thy holy Name, and the everlaſting comfort of our own Souls.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:174612:32"/>
               <head>Meditations for <hi>Friday,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Lord, even the moſt mighty God hath ſpoken, and called the world, from the riſing up of the Sun unto the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down thereof.</p>
               <p>Out of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on hath God appeared in perfect beauty.</p>
               <p>Our God ſhall com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſhall not keep ſilence; there ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll go before him a conſuming fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and a mighty tempeſt ſhall be ſtirred up round about him.</p>
               <p>He ſhall call the Heaven from above, and the Earth, that he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y judge his People.</p>
               <p>Gather my Saints together unto me: thoſe that have made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with me with Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>And the Heavens ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll declare his Righteouſneſs; for God is Judge himſelf.</p>
               <p>Hear, O my People, and I will ſpeak: I my ſelf will teſtifie againſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:174612:32"/> thee, O Iſrael; for I am God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thy God.</p>
               <p>I will not reprove thee becauſe of thy Sacrifices, or for thy Burnt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offerings; becauſe they were not always before me.</p>
               <p>I will take no Bullock out of thine houſe, nor He-goats out of thy fold.</p>
               <p>For all the Beaſts of the Foreſt are mine, and ſo are the Cattle upon a thouſand hills.</p>
               <p>I know all the Fowls upon the mountains: and the wild Beaſts of the field are in my ſight.</p>
               <p>If I be hungry, I will not tell thee; for the whole world is mine, and all that is therein.</p>
               <p>Thinkeſt thou that I will eat Bulls fleſh, and drink the blood of Goats?</p>
               <p>Offer unto God thankſgiving; and pay thy vows unto the moſt higheſt.</p>
               <p>And call upon me in the time of trouble; ſo will I hear thee, and thou ſhalt praiſe me.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:174612:33"/>
               <p>But unto the ungodly, ſaid God, why doſt thou preach my Laws, and takeſt my Covenant in thy mouth?</p>
               <p>Whereas thou hateſt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and haſt caſt my Words behind thee.</p>
               <p>When thou ſaweſt a thief, thou conſentedſt unto him; and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt been partaker with the Adulterers.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt let thy mouth ſpeak wickedneſs, and with thy tongue thou haſt ſet forth deceit.</p>
               <p>Thou ſateſt and ſpakeſt againſt thy Brother; yea, and haſt ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thine own Mother's Son.</p>
               <p>Theſe things haſt thou done, and I held my tongue: and thou thoughteſt wickedly, that I am even ſuch a one as they ſelf; but I will reprove thee, and ſet before thee the things that thou haſt done.</p>
               <p>O conſider this, ye that forg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t God, leſt I pluck you away, and there be none to deliver you.</p>
               <p>Whoſo offereth me thanks and praiſe, he honoureth me: and to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:174612:33"/> him that ordereth his converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aright, will I ſhew the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Friday</hi> Morning: A Confeſſion of Sins.</head>
               <p>O Moſt mighty and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God, I preſume to preſent my ſelf this Morning before thy Divine Majeſty, to offer up unto thee this my early ſacrifice; but in the performance of it, I make known my unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and diſcloſe my Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and exceedingly diſcover my imperfections and wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>For, alas, I draw near unto thee with my lips, but my heart is far from thee; I call upon thee with my tongue, but my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:174612:34"/> ſoul at the ſame time commits wickedneſs againſt thee: My righteouſneſs comes ſhort of the Scribes and Phariſees, and are but as filthy Rags: my holineſs but as a morning Dew, yea all my actions of Devotion (if weighed in thy Balance) are but abomination in thy ſight: From the ſoal of the Foot, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the crown of the Head, I am altogether polluted and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean; yea nothing to be found in me but wounds, and putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſores, imprinted and ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into my ſoul and fleſh by the cuſtom of my Sin.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <p>My Eyes are full of Vanity, my Ears full of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niquity, my Hands of Impurity, my Will perverſe to that which is Good, my Remembrance affable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd pleaſing to that which is Evil,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:174612:34"/> my Underſtanding is darkned, my Conſcience ſeared, my Head full of miſchief, my feet ſwift to ſhed blood; Deſtruction and Wickedneſs are in all my ways, and the way of Peace have I not known.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Since then, O Lord, that my Sins are ſo great and grievous againſt thy Law and againſt thy Goſpel, if thou ſhouldeſt be ſo extream as to mark againſt me what I have done amiſs, who is able to abide it? If thou ſhouldſt call me ſuddenly to a ſtrict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, how ſhould I ſhew my Face? If I deny waht is laid to my charge, my Conſcience will accuſe me; If I forſwear, the dumb and ſenſeleſs Creatures will bear witneſs againſt me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Whom have I in Heaven but
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:174612:35"/> thee, and there is no Friend in the Earth beneath, which I have in compariſon of thee, no other Mediator amongſt Men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but even thine only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son Chriſt Jeſus, in whom only thou art well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? by the virtue of whoſe Death and Paſſion, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of whoſe precious blood, which trickled down from his ſide, waſh me from my ſins; and beſprinkle my polluted Heart from an evil Conſcience.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>And I beſeech thee O Lord, not only to waſh away my ſins with the blood of thine imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Lamb, but alſo to purge my heart by thine only Spirit, from the droſs of my natural Corruptions, that I may feel thy Spirit more and more, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sin in the power &amp; practice
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:174612:35"/> thereof; ſo that I may with more freedom of mind and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of will, ſerve thee the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> living God, in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs this Day, and all the days of my Life, for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Friday</hi> Noon: For God's Direction.</head>
               <p>O Lord moſt holy, I beſeech thee to direct all my ways, correct my wanderings, and erect my wild and worldly Thoughts unto thee, the God of my Salvation. Learn me that divine Art of living in thy Fear, to labour in thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and evermore run ſwiftly in the ways of thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Direct my Thoughts, Words and Works; preſerve and bleſs me in my going out and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:174612:36"/> coming in; and grant that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever my heart ſhall think, my tongue utter, or my hands ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe this day, may tend to the glory of thy holy Name, the good of others, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of my own Conſcience.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>End theſe ſinful days; O bleſſed Redeemer, and haſten thy coming; and give me Grace to ſtand ready prepared to meet thee, who art the ſweet Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom of my Soul; that at thy coming, whether it be by the hour of Death, or at the day of Judgment, I may joyfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce thoſe bleſſed words of, Come, Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> come quickly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Deliver me, O Lord, from all thoſe heavy Judgments which hang over my head as due unto me for my Tranſgreſſions: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:174612:36"/> them as far from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in diſtance, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt; bury them all in thy Grave, that they neither riſe to ſhame me in this Life, nor condemn me in the World to come: To whom be aſcribed for thine infinite Mercy, all Honour, Praiſe and Glory, from this time forth and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Friday</hi> Night: Againſt carnal Security.</head>
               <p>O Merciful Father, I here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate my ſelf in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and reverence of heart and mind, beſeeching thee to guide and protect me this Night with thy bleſſed Spirit, and though my ſinful fleſh ſhall ſlumber and ſleep, yet grant that my Soul may continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:174612:37"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Let not the Enemy come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me unawares and find me ſlumbering or ſleeping, as rocked in the Cradle of carnal Security; leſt I being unarm'd and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of thy favour and help, he enter into the Houſe of my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Body, and their takes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of my leprous Soul; and endanger both to be thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lake which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Make me to conſider that my Bed is but a pattern of the Grave, and that when I lay my ſelf down in it, I cannot riſe up unleſs thy heavenly Providence enables me. Teach me to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that ſleep is the very Figure and Image of Death, to whoſe ſtroak at thy appointed time, I muſt ſubmit and reſign
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:174612:37"/> my ſelf; endue me with Love and Charity to all Men; let my Lamp, O Lord, be filled with freſh Oil, that whenſoever thy Meſſenger, Death, approaches, and knocks at the Gate of this mortal Body, I may at his Summons in the day of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead, be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to attend on thee my Bride with my Lamp burning.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Let me be ever mindful of the great and laſt day, wherein I muſt render an account of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very idle thought, word, and work, and grant I may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as with a Wedding-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt the time that thou, O Lord, ſhalt call for me out of this ſinful World. In the mean time, let me fly from Sin as from a Serpent, and from
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:174612:38"/> unrighteouſneſs as from a Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrice, and above all things ſeek thy Glory; and when this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Life is ended I may be made partaker of Immortality, and Life Eternal, in thy moſt bleſſed and glorious Kingdom.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Let thy Mercy and Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs follow me, O Lord, all the days of my Life, that I may dwell in thy Houſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore praiſe thy holy Name? grant that I may in the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of thy greatneſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my own unworthineſs; and viſit me, O Lord, by driving from me all the Aſſaults of my Enemies, both ghoſtly and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Let thy holy Angel be with me, to keep me this Night, and evermore; fit me for the duties
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:174612:38"/> of the next day, if it be thy heavenly will to ſpare me this Night<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this, O Lord, I beg at thy merciful Hands, through the Merits and Mediation of my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who liveth and reigneth with thee, and the Holy Ghoſt, now and for ever.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>Meditations for <hi>Saturday.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Will cry unto God with my voice; even unto God will I cry with my voice, and he ſhall hearken unto me.</p>
               <p>In the time of my trouble I ſought the Lord: my ſore ran and ceaſed not in the night ſeaſon my Soul refuſed comfort.</p>
               <p>When I am in heavineſs, I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l think upon God; when my heart is vexed I will complain.</p>
               <p>Thou holdeſt mine eyes waking; I am ſo feeble that I cannot ſpeak.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:174612:39"/>
               <p>I have conſidered the days of old, and the years that are paſt.</p>
               <p>I call to remembrance my Song; and in the night I commune with mine own heart, and ſearch out my Spirits.</p>
               <p>Will the Lord abſent himſelf for ever? and will he be no more intreated?</p>
               <p>Is his mercy clean gone for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? and his Promiſe come utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to an end for evermore?</p>
               <p>Hath God forgotten to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious? and will he ſhut up his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſs in diſpleaſure?</p>
               <p>And I ſaid it is mine own infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; but I will remember the years of the right hand of the moſt higheſt.</p>
               <p>I will remember the works of the Lord, and call to mind thy wonders of old time.</p>
               <p>I will think alſo of all thy works; and my talking ſhall be of thy doings.</p>
               <p>Thy way, O God, is holy: who
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:174612:39"/> is ſo great a God as our God?</p>
               <p>Thou art the God that doſt wonders, and haſt declared thy power among the people.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt mightily delivered thy people; even the Sons of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob and Joſeph.</p>
               <p>The Waters ſaw thee, O God, the Waters ſaw thee and were afraid; the Depths were troubled.</p>
               <p>The Clouds alſo poured out Water, the Air thundred, and thine Arrows went abroad.</p>
               <p>The voice of thy Thunder was heard round about; the Lightning ſhone upon the Ground, the Earth was moved, and ſhook withal.</p>
               <p>Thy way is in the Sea and thy paths in the great Waters; and thy footſteps are not known.</p>
               <p>Thou leadeſt thy People like Sheep by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:174612:40"/>
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Saturday</hi> Morning: For God's Providence.</head>
               <p>MOſt gracious God, I yield thee humble and hearty thanks for preſerving and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending me this night paſt from all thoſe Perils and Dangers, which poor Duſt and Aſhes are ſubject to fall into. Had I not been preſerved by thy almighty Providence, I had long ſince, both Body and Soul, been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into everlaſting Perdition; but thou art a God infinite in Mercy, and whoſe compaſſions fail not towards poor Sinners, by ſupporting them in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral neceſſities.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Vouchſafe, O Lord, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give whatſoever I have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt thy divine Majeſty
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:174612:40"/> this Night, either ſleeping or waking; or at any other time, ſecretly or openly: Grant unto me unfeigned Repentance, and newneſs of Life; open unto me, O Lord, that ever-ſtreaming Fountain, which thou haſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened for Sinners, even the Blood of thy dear Son Chriſt Jeſus; and which thou haſt promiſed under the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to open to the penitent of the Houſe of <hi>David.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Give unto me thy holy Spirit which thou haſt promiſed to give (to the World's end) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thine elect People, and let the ſame thine holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter purge my heart, heal my Corruptions, ſanctifie my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and conſecrate my Soul and Body, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lively Temples, to ſerve
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:174612:41"/> thee in Righteouſneſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs all the days of my Life. Give me, I earneſtly beſeech thee, a ſupply of all thoſe Graces I ſtand in need of, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all thoſe good Gifts thou haſt endowed me with.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>As thou haſt now wakened my Body from Sleep, ſo, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, rouſe my Soul from the ſleep of Sin and carnal Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; give me Grace, as a Child of Light, to walk in all holy Obedience before thee this day; and grant me to endeavour to keep Faith and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards Thee, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>To this end I recommend my ſelf, with all my ways, thoughts, words, and actions, (together with all that belongs to me)
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:174612:41"/> unto thy divine Protection, praying thee to keep both them and me from all Evil, and to give a Bleſſing to all my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings this Day, and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Saturday</hi> Noon: For Tranquility of Spirit.</head>
               <p>O Moſt merciful God, and loving Father, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeſt all the dwellers upon Earth; and none can live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy arm of Providence ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports him: No ſooner do I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon the Affairs of this World, but I am ſurrounded about with a cloud of Miſeries; the Fleſh provokes me to Luſt, the World allures me to Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and the Devil tempts me to commit all manner of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:174612:42"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Fears of Enemies abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright me, Wrongs of ill Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours do oppreſs me, Cares for the things of this Life do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume me, and even all the day long ſomething or other doth afflict and torment me. Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity on the one hand frets me, and Proſperity on the other hand flatters me. Over my head Heaven's Vengeance, due to my Sins, is ready to fall hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy upon me; and under my feet Hell gapes ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Amidſt thoſe many toils and perplexities, where to find reſt I know not, or to fly for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, but to thee, O Lord, moſt holy and mighty; direct me and guide me in theſe difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, protect me from theſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:174612:42"/> and dangers, ſettle me in a courſe of Godlineſs, and let me walk, ſoberly and circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as becometh a Good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, ſpending and ending that ſmall remnant of days which thou haſt allotted me in this World, in thy Fear and Service.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Teach me ſo to number my days, that I may apply my heart unto true Wiſdom. Make me wiſe unto Salvation, ſimple to that which is Evil, and prone to that which is Good. Fructifie me unto good works, and grant that I may be Charitable, Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Conſcionable towards all men, now and for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:174612:43"/>
               <head>A Prayer for <hi>Saturday</hi> Night: For Remiſſion of Sins.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, I humbly beſeech thee to bury all my Sins and Tranſgreſſions in thy Grave, which I have committed from my Infancy, unto this preſent, againſt thy divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. Be thou, O Lord, my light in darkneſs, then ſhall my light ſhine clear as the day.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>O God, the Father of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, have mercy upon me, and bleſs me; O God, the Son, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of all the World, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and keep me; O holy and bleſſed Spirit, proceeding from the Father and the Son, deliver me this Night from all Sin and Evil; O holy bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trinity, Three Perſons
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:174612:43"/> and One God, direct, guide, and ſanctifie me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Be thou my protector and defender amidſt all dangers, that when I lay me down to reſt, I may fear no Evil: And grant, O Lord, at my laſt hour thy ſpiritual illumination; that when my ſtrength faileth, and the light of my Eyes is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from me, mine Ears wax deaf, and my Mouth dumb, and all my ſenſes have forſaken me; then infuſe ſome ſenſe into me of eternal Life, that I may taſte and reliſh, in this mortal Body, the beginning of thy everlaſting Comfort; that at my departure out of this World, I may, by the Eye of Faith, behold the divine Preſence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Open my Eyes more and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:174612:44"/> more, that I may diſcern the wonderous works of thy Law; and open thou, O Lord, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe my Lips, that my Mouth and Tongue may ſhew forth thy Praiſe, and extol thy great and glorious Name. Prepare my Heart, O Lord, I beſeech thee, for thy divine Service, this next day following: It is thy holy-day; O fit me for the ſanctifying of the ſame, that I may not ſpend it on my Luſts and the pleaſures of Sin, but dedicate it wholly to thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Let my chief delight be to ceaſe from the works of Sin, as well as from my worldly Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, that I may, through thy Bleſſing, feel in my Heart the beginning of that eternal Sabbath, which is Joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:174612:44"/> and full of Glory. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, O Lord, my heart in thy Fear, and guide and ſteer all the whole courſe of my Life in thy Favour: Fit and prepare me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the hour of Death, and day of Diſſolution, that if thou ſhouldeſt this Night make my Bed in the Grave of Silence, I may live and die unto thee, who liveſt for ever; to whom be aſcribed all Power and Glory, Adoration and Subjection, now and for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="confession">
               <head>An humble Confeſſion of Sins, before the moſt holy Sacrament of the Lord's Supper.</head>
               <p>O Moſt holy Lord God, who, according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy tender Mercies, doſt put away the Sins of all thoſe that truly repent, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:174612:45"/> them no more. Open, O Lord, I beſeech thee, the Eyes of thy boundleſs Mercy, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Compaſſion upon me, the moſt unworthy of all thy Servants: from the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of my heart I earneſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore thy pardon and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for all my paſt Sins and Offences; the number of them exceeds the ordinary expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Mercy, and are ſo heinous that they can plead no excuſe: the ſad Account being caſt up, is no leſs than the breach of all thy holy Commandments, both in Thought, Word, and Deed: thy Mercy and Goodneſs, which ſhould have led me to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, I have abuſed: I have ſlighted thy Judgments, and thy Puniſhments have I not feared; I have utterly neglected the means of my own Salvation,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:174612:45"/> and by my Wickedneſs have moſt grievouſly provoked thy Wrath and Indignation againſt me? my Life which ſhould have been wholly devoted to thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I have miſpent in the deſire and ſinful Luſts of the Fleſh: my ways have been evil, and that continually; the ſecret cogitations of my heart moſt wicked, and ſo deteſtable hath the whole courſe of my Life been, that my heart is vexed within me, and my ſoul trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth to look up to heaven for Mercy, for fear of thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. If therefore thou O Lord, ſhouldſt be extream to mark what I have done amiſs, and take Vengeance for my Sins, I ſhould be as Chaff before the face of the Wind, and in Juſtice might be ſwept away into the place of everlaſting Torment.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:174612:46"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>But, O Lord, from thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver flowing Fountain there is Mercy, that thou may'ſt be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; thou art a God of all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Conſolation, a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, loving, and gracious Father, ready and willing to hear all penitent Sinners, that with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Repentance, and true Faith come unto thee: I come unto thee therefore, in the name of Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous, thy beloved Son, and my bleſſed Redeemer; I humbly proſtrate my ſelf before the Throne of thy Mercy-ſeat, provided with no other hope but what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the greatneſs of thy Clemency; for his ſake only have Mercy upon me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>In all humility of Spirit, and with hearty Contrition, I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:174612:46"/> my Soul and Body to thy Goodneſs, beſeeching thee not to let my Sins be as a Cloud to intercept between my Prayers and thy Pity, thy Goodneſs and my neceſſities: blot all my Tranſgreſſions out of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, the Sins of my Youth, or Sins of my Age; Sins of my Body, or Sins of my Soul; the Sins that I know, and the Sins that I know not; Sins of Remiſsneſs, Omiſſion, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; all notorious and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Sins; Sins of Pride, Envy, Hatred, Malice, and all Uncharitableneſs; [<hi>here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thy particular Sins</hi>] from all which, good Lord deliver me; and grant me a full and a free Pardon, perfect Remiſſion and Abſolution for the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>As one deep calleth upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:174612:47"/> with the prophet <hi>David,</hi> out of the Depth of my Miſery, I cry unto thee for the depth of thy Mercy. O Lord, hear my Petitions, and hold not thy peace at my Tears: conſider the Contrition of my Heart, and the Sorrow of my Soul; and by the Merits of his moſt precious Blood that was ſo plentifully ſhed upon the Croſs for all Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Sinners, and True Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, waſh away the multitude of my Tranſgreſſions, that my Soul, by thy Mercy, being clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the guilt of Sin, I may be found a worthy partaker and receiver of this holy and divine Myſtery.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>And now, O holy Lord, that I am about to receive the bleſſed Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, how ſhall
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:174612:47"/> I, that am ſo great a Sinner, Duſt and Aſhes, dare to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and come into thy Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, or to approach thy holy Table! Thou in whoſe ſight the very Heavens are not clear, and the Pillars of the Earth ſhake at thy Preſence. What then ſhall become of me, poor, wretched, and miſerable, that I am! but O thou that art the true Balm of <hi>Gilead,</hi> haſt left us a command in thy holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laiden, and I will give you reſt,</hi> Matth. 11. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Upon which Command, I come, O Lord, unto thee at this time, in a confident Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy Promiſe in Chriſt Jeſus, thou wilt have Mercy upon me, eaſe and refreſh my Soul, that is wearied with the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:174612:48"/> burthen of my Sins; waſh me and cleanſe me throughly from all my Wickedneſs, and renew a right Spirit within me. Direct me in this great Myſtery with a reverend and awful dread of thy Majeſty, that all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of my Soul and Body may rightly apprehend, and joyfully receive this eternal Food, this Bread of Life: And grant me thy heavenly Grace, that I may obtain the virtue, fruit, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of my Saviour's Death and Paſſion, with a full remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all my Sins, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Salvation, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before the Sacrament.</head>
               <p>O Moſt gracious God, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee, help thy Servant, whom of thy great
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:174612:48"/> Mercy thou haſt created out of nothing; repair the ruins of my Soul, and enlarge the frame of my Underſtanding; cleanſe it from all filthy Corruptions, and ſupply it with all heavenly Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that it may be both conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently fit and furniſhed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thee, who art a God of all Purity: O Make an entry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Heart and take thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence there for ever; poſſeſs that which is thine own, both by Creation, Redemption, and Merits of that bitter Death and Paſſion, through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving after Receiving of the bleſſed Sacrament.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, I praiſe thee for my Creation, Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption and Preſervation; and by
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:174612:49"/> whoſe Grace and Mercy I hope to be glorified; more-eſpecially for feeding me this Day with the precious Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt. I will therefore offer unto thee the Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, and always praiſe thy holy Name, beſeeching thee to pour upon my Heart the ſweet Streams of thy Mercy: Conform my Life, confirm my Faith, and let thy Grace evermore guide me, that I may with a ſtrong aſſurance of thine infallible Truth, and promiſed Mercy, vanquiſh and ſubdue whatſoever rebelleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy bleſſed will.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Keep holy my Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſuffer them not to be defiled through delectation of Sin; but that my full delight and joy may be in thee, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:174612:49"/> walk before thee in ſincerity of Heart and godly Converſation, that I may here on Earth glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy Name, and after this Life, with all thy falthful flock, poſſeſs that everlaſting Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which thy Son, Chriſt Jeſus hath purchaſed with his moſt precious blood. To whom with thee, and the Holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glory, world without end.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>John 5. 14.</bibl>
                     <q>Behold thou art made whole, ſin no more leaſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>Jude 25.</bibl>
                     <q>To the only wiſe God our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, be Glory and Majeſty. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Power, both now and ever <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:174612:50"/>
               <head>A Morning Prayer for a Private Perſon.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, and moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Father, I thine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Servant do in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity proſtrate my ſelf before thy divine Majeſty, acknowledging my own Vileneſs, natural Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and abominable Sins, which from time to time have been committed againſt thee. I am unworthy, O Lord, to appear in thy holy Temple, or approach the remoteſt limits of the Place where thine Honour dwelleth.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>But I beſeech thee, for the ſake of thy dearly beloved Son, accept of this my morning Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving for thy manifold Mercies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:174612:50"/> towards me this Night paſt, and heretofore till this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For my Reſt, Food, Raiment, Health, Peace, and Liberty, with the hopes of a better Life when this is ended: Continue thy all ſupplying mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies unto me this day. Govern me with thy Fear, and compaſs me about with thy Favour; ſet all my Sins to that accompt, which thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, my only Saviour hath made up for them upon the Croſs, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lay any of them to my charge, but freely forgive and forget them all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Proſper, O Lord, all that I ſhall take in hand this Day; let my directions proceed from thy holy Will, and the ſucceſs from thy merciful Hand: Give me a Competency for maintenance
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:174612:51"/> in this mortal Life, that I may with quietneſs of mind, and thankfulneſs of heart, paſs my time in this vale of miſery, in doing good to all men according to my ability, without diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to my ſelf or harm to others.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Grant theſe things, O Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, and whatever elſe thou ſeeſt moſt neceſſary for me, and all other thy Servants in the World, for the good of our Souls and Bodies; guide and conduct me in the doing and performing diligently thoſe things that thou haſt required of me; and that the end of all my labours may tend to the Praiſe of thy holy Name, and the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of my poor Brethren. Grant this good Lord, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:174612:51"/>
               <head>An Evening Prayer for a Private Perſon.</head>
               <p>O Almighty and everlaſting God, I do confeſs I am unworthy of the leaſt of all thy Mercies; yet being bound in duty, for thy preſervation of me this day paſt, and all the time of my whole Life, I offer up unto thee Praiſe and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for my Election, Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Redemption, Vocation, and Sanctification, with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gifts and Graces appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Life, or that which is to come.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>O thou that ſitteſt above the Cherubims, my tongue and lips ſhall praiſe and glorifie thee, for preſerving me by thy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence this Day paſt, from ſo
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:174612:52"/> many Miſeries and Caſualties, which I might juſtly have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into, hadſt thou entred into Judgment with me. But thou art a God full of Mercy and Compaſſion, and paſſeſt by Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, to win me the more by thy patience and long-ſuffering: make me truly thankful for thy Mercies, ready and willing to make a good improvement of thy moſt gracious Forbearance, and careful to obey thy Will with Conſcience, Diligence, and Conſtancy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Strengthen me from above with thy mighty hand, to walk in every good way without fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and to bring forth the Fruits of a true and lively Faith in my Life and Converſation, all the days of my ſojourning here. Arm me with thy Grace
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:174612:52"/> and holy Spirit, againſt the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and Vanities of the World, and Wiles and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Devil, and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of the Fleſh; and ſo ſettle and frame my mind to the continual exerciſe of devout Prayer, hearing of thy ſacred Word, and watching for thy coming, both in publick and private.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Keep me, O Lord, this night from all Evils which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, either to my Body, or my Soul: Extend thy Goodneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all thoſe that have any dependance upon me; give me ſweet and comfortable reſt, that when I ſhall awake, all my Thoughts &amp; Meditations may be on thee, and thy Law. Bleſs me, O Lord, all the nights and days of my Life, and at the end
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:174612:53"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:174612:53"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:174612:54"/> thereof, ſend me a bleſſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and afterwards a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Reſurrection both of Soul and Body, unto Life eternal; grant theſe things, O heavenly Father for thy Son Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, my only Saviour.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Morning Prayer for a Private Family.</head>
               <p>O Almighty and moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Father, thou haſt promiſed, That where Two or Three are gathered together in thy Name, thou wilt be in the midſt of them, we poor ſinful Creatures, duſt and aſhes, here in all humility do proſtrate our Bodies and Souls before thee as living Monuments of thy Mercy. We are unworthy of the leaſt of thy mercies, yet haſt thou from time to time
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:174612:54"/> made us partakers of many, for which we praiſe and magnifie thy holy Name, beſeeching thee to give us underſtanding Hearts, to be ſenſible of our Evils, with direction and aſſiſtance from thy holy Spirit to avoid the ſame.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>And as thou haſt, O Lord, kept us this Night, in the time of darkneſs and dangers, ſo we beſeech thee to preſerve us this Day, that the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs may rule in our Hearts, and all the darkneſs that lurketh in them may be ſcattered, to the comfort of our own Souls in the day of our Lord Jeſus. Endue us with thoſe Gifts and Graces thou ſeeſt to be moſt needful for us, and grant that with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Hearts &amp; pure Conſciences, we may wholly employ them in thy ſervice to thy honour and glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:174612:55"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Continue to us, we earneſtly beſeech thee, thy bleſſing of Health, Peace, and Maintenance, ſo far as thou ſeeſt them conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for us; chaſe away from us all Rancour and Malice, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, Uncharitableneſs, and Unkindneſs, and whatſoever is contrary to thy Law; take from us all Ignorance and Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and prevent all thoſe things that thou knoweſt may hinder us in our Chriſtian Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or Employment: Encreaſe our Faith, Patience and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and let thy Bleſſing be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this whole Family; guide us in thy Truth, protect us in our Ways, and all thoſe whom thou haſt made dear unto us, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be preſent or abſent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Give us Grace, by thy Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:174612:55"/> to fear thee more carefully, and to grieve for our ſins more heartily; let our minds be ſet upon thee, and give us ſuch hearts as we may learn ſomething of every thing, and make a Spiritual uſe of all our Earthly Affairs here till we come to dwell with thee in the Kingdom of Glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs, O Lord, the univerſal Church, with Truth, Peace and Unity, Soundneſs of Doctrine, and holy Diſcipline; Preſerve our gracious Sovereign, and all the Royal Family; Bleſs his Majeſty's moſt honourable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Council, and all others in Authority, with neceſſary Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs all Schools of Learning and good Education, eſpecially
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:174612:56"/> the two Univerſities of this Land: Bleſs this City and Place wherein we live; remove the Puniſhment due for the Sins thereof, and give them a double portion of thy Grace, to repent in time, before the Deſtroyer enters again amongſt them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs all our Friends, Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or others, for whom thou haſt appointed us to make Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Supplications; ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them that lie upon their Beds of Sickneſs, ſend them the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and help of thy Spirit, that lie in anguiſh of Conſcience for remorſe of Sin, and convert all thoſe that go aſtray from thy Commandments; teach us by their Examples to view our own Weakneſs, and to walk more circumſpectly for the time to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:174612:56"/>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs this Family with Grace and Peace, that all of them, from the higheſt to the loweſt, may know their ſeveral Duties, and may rightly and duly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe the ſame in thy fear, and unto thy glory, through Jeſus Chriſt, our only Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>An Evening Prayer for a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Family.</head>
               <p>OEternal God, the Father of Mercies, and great Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Heaven and Earth, we render thee humble and hearty Thanks for thy merciful Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of us this Day, and all the whole courſe of our Lives; that thou haſt brought us ſafe through ſo many Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Difficulties we might
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:174612:57"/> juſtly have fallen into, had not thy Arm of Providence been ſtretched out to ſupport us.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Morning and Evening thou takeſt care of us, and heapeſt upon us ſo many Bleſſings and Benefits, both Spiritual and Temporal; yet we neither fear thee nor ſerve thee, as we ought to do; but thou art a God ſlow to anger, and of great pity, and art ready to forgive our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Sins, which we from time to time have committed againſt thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Good Lord, we beſeech thee keep us evermore from day to day, as thou haſt done, and make us conſtant in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy holy Name, and the practiſe of thy Law, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Malice of Man, nor
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:174612:57"/> Subtilty of Satan be able to make us turn away from thee, Lord, turn thy Face from our Sins, even from thoſe Sins where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have ſo much delighted; take from us thoſe hearts of Stone, and give us hearts of Fleſh, and waſh and cleanſe our poluted Souls in the Blood of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Forgive us all that is paſt, and grant us the aſſurance of that Forgiveneſs, ſealed up by the holy Spirit in our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; Oh kindle thy love more and more in our hearts, that we may never depart from thee, but attain unto a due thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for thy benefits, and a moſt unfeigned and earneſt Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for all our Sins and Tranf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:174612:58"/>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Suffer us not to cloſe our Eyes till our Souls have reckoned and made even for all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences which not only this day, but all the former minutes of our lives, we have committed againſt thy divine Majeſty: Give thine Angels charge over us, that at what hour ſoever thou calleſt us out of this Vale of Tears, where we do but travail and toil all the day long, we may not be found to be idle Loiterers in thy Harveſt, but good and acceptable Servants, having Oil in our Lamps, and on us the Robe of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Wedding-Garment of Regeneration, that we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to encounter Death, the King of Terrors, to meet our bleſſed Lord in the Clouds, when he cometh to Judgment,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:174612:58"/> and to follow the Lamb where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Expel and remove far away from us all wicked Spirits, and graciouſly protect us from our Perſecutors, which lay Snares to ſubdue us; do thou, O God, aſſiſt us, that we may peaceably ſleep and reſt in thee: hide us in thy Tabernacle, from the ſtrife of all Men, and keep us that we may fear no Evil. O thou that neither ſlumbereſt nor ſleepeſt, let thy Rod and Staff evermore comfort and defend us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>Let thy mighty Hand and ſtretched out Arm, O Lord, be ſtill our Defence; thy Mercy and Loving-kindneſs in thy beloved Son, our Salvation; thy true and holy Word our Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:174612:59"/> thy Grace and holy Spirit our Comfort and Conſolation: Let thy Mercy, O God, prevent and follow us all the days of our Lives, that we may dwell in thy Houſe of Defence, in length of days, praiſing thee evermore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Let thy Bleſſing be upon all of us within this Houſhold, guide us in our Ways, and lead us into thy Truth: Bleſs our Parents, Kindred and Friends, whereſoever diſperſed, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever linked unto us: Be a merciful Judge unto us, and continually protect us from the ſnares of Satan the Old Serpent; and finally conduct us into the ſociety of Angels, and of all Saints, in thy holy Paradiſe; to whom be aſcribed, as is moſt due to thee the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, one true, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:174612:59"/> and everlaſting God, all Honour, Power, and Glory, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, now and for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>Meditations for the Sick.</head>
               <p>O Lord rebuke me not in thine Indignation; neither cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten me in thy heavy Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>Have mercy upon me, O Lord, for I am weak. O Lord heal me for my Bones are vexed.</p>
               <p>My Soul is alſo ſore troubled; But, Lord, how long wilt thou puniſh me?</p>
               <p>Turn thee, O Lord, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my Soul; O ſave me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
               <p>For in death no Man remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth thee, and who will give thee thanks in the Pit?</p>
               <p>I am weary of my groaning, every night waſh I my Bed, and water my Couch with my Tears.</p>
               <p>My Beauty is gone for very trouble; and worn away becauſe of all mine Enemies.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:174612:60"/>
               <p>Away from me all ye that work Vanity, for the Lord hath heard the voice of my weeping.</p>
               <p>The Lord hath heard my Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Lord will receive my Prayer.</p>
               <p>Hearken unto my voice, O Lord, when I cry unto thee; have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon me, and hear me.</p>
               <p>O hide not thou thy face from me, nor caſt thy Servant away in Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt been my ſuccour, leave me not, neither forſake me, O God of my Salvation.</p>
               <p>What profit is there in my blood when I go down to the Pit?</p>
               <p>Shall the duſt give thanks unto thee? or ſhall it declare thy truth?</p>
               <p>Hear, O Lord, and have mercy upon me: Lord, be thou my helper.</p>
               <p>Shew thy Servant the light of thy Countenance; and ſave me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:174612:60"/>
               <head>A Prayer in time of Sickneſs.</head>
               <p>O Almighty and ever-living God, in whoſe hands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the life of all Mankind, and who correcteſt every Son, whom thou receiveſt; merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I humble beſeech thee to hear my voice, and deſpiſe not the Prayer I make now unto thee, in the time of trouble: In the vexation of my Spirit, and in the very anguiſh of my Soul, I cry unto thee for mercy.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>O thou that haſt created, and made me of nothing, and haſt redeemed me from the ſlavery of Sin, Death and Hell, by the moſt precious Blood of thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt, which was ſpilt upon the Croſs for my Sins, Have mercy upon me: Bow
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:174612:61"/> down thine all-hearing Ear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my complaint, and caſt me not away in thy fierce anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>My Sins cry aloud to Heaven for Vengeance, and I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved thy wrath and heavy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt me: Thou haſt caſt me down upon the Bed of Sickneſs, and I begin to fall as leaves beaten with a vehement wind; yet thy Chaſtiſments are leſs than my deſervings; but of thy mercy and goodneſs, O Lord, correct me not to death, but to amendment of Life, for thine own ſake, for thy holy Name's ſake, for thy Son Chriſt Jeſus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke, be merciful unto my Sins, for they are great.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Spare thy Servant, good Lord, which confeſſeth his Sins unto thee, pour the Oil of thy ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:174612:61"/> Grace into my Heart, and work thereby in me a true and immediate Repentance and reſtore me again to thy favour, according to thy gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to humble Penitents; let thy merciful Providence ſo guide and govern me in this affliction thou haſt been pleaſed to lay upon me, that I may never fall into utter darkneſs, ignorance of thee, or inconſideration of my ſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Let the faintneſs of my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Condemnation of my ſelf be overcome by thy ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable Light; thou that art the God of all conſolation, grant that I may be mindful of the great account I have to make at the day of Judgment, and that I may bear in mind the reward which is due to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:174612:62"/> the faithful, the end of miſery, and the beginning of all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but to the ſecure and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the beginning of eternal puniſhment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Strengthen my Faith, accept my penitential Tears, ſpeak peace to my Soul and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and ſay, Thou art my Salvation, then let thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit deſcend into my Heart, with this expreſs, <hi>My Grace is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for thee;</hi> then ſhall my Heart leap for joy, and my Soul ſhall be exceeding glad, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to be diſſolved, and be at peace, that after this frail mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Life is ended, I may enjoy the eternal fruition of they hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Preſence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>Suffer me not, O Lord, in this my trial, to be poſſeſs'd
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:174612:62"/> with a fear of Condemnation, or to deſpond of thy Promiſes; but in ſure conſidence of heart apply to my ſelf the remiſſion of all my Sins, that at the laſt hour, by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, I may enjoy a taſt of eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Let not Death (if thou art pleaſed to ſend it) be terrible or bitter unto me; but when it cometh, I may rejoicingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the fame; and having eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the ſtorm of Temptation, and the dangers of Satan, I may triumph like a Conqueror, and behold the Power and Preſence of thy holy Spirit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Let my laſt words be the ſame which thy Son did utter upon the Croſs, ſaying, <hi>Father, into thy hands I commend my Spirit;</hi> and when my Speech is departed from me, hear the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:174612:63"/> groanings, and ſighs of my Heart, and the deſire of my Soul, that at the laſt thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant may depart in Peace, and reach thoſe heavenly Manſions prepared for him: My Soul, O Lord, heartily deſireth to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to that ſupernatural City whereof ſuch glorious things are ſpoken.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="part">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>Breathe inward Comforts to my Heart; tho' my Body be going the way of all Fleſh, yet let my Soul go the way of all Saints. Lord, hear me and help me, ſtand by me and ſave me, and if thou haſt determined to lay my Body into the Grave, receive my Soul into thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to reſt in joy and peace for evermore, through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:174612:63"/>
               <head>A Prayer to be ſaid by thoſe that viſit the Sick.</head>
               <p>O Moſt gracious God, who haſt Compaſſion upon all Men, and hateſt nothing that thou haſt made, mercifully we beſeech thee to have Compaſſion on this thy Servant, who by thy Viſitation hath been ſorely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and by the ſame even brought to the end of his Days, and period of his Life; be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therefore, good Lord, to have Mercy upon him, accept of him as the work of thine own Hands, a Lamb of thy Fold, thy Servant redeemed by Jeſus Chriſt, who is willing, by thy appointment, to leave this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable World, in full aſſurance of thy Mercy in Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of his Sins.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:174612:64"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Guide him, good Lord, in this his laſt Journey, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quit of all the troubles of this tranſitory Life, he may be ſafely conducted by thy power to the Heaven of Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs into the Arms of bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Mercy, to everlaſting Peace and perpetual Joys, there to reign with all the Company of bleſſed Saints and Angels with thee in continual Bliſs for evermore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>And, gracious God, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, by thy abundant Goodneſs, by the multitude of thy tender Mercies, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions, by the Merits of thy bitter Death and bloody Paſſion, by thy glorious Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, and by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of thy holy &amp; bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, have mercy upon him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:174612:64"/> him from the burthen and guilt of his Sins, from the fears and terrors of Death, and from the fury and power of Hell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Lift thou up the light of thy Countenance upon him, that in all the pains of his Body, in all the agonies of his Spirit, let thy Comforts refreſh his Soul, and enable him patiently to wait till his Change ſhall come: And grant, O Lord, that when this earthly Houſe and Tabernacle of his Body ſhall be diſſolv'd, he may have a Building of God, an Houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens; and that for his ſake, who by his moſt precious Blood hath purchaſed Salvation for all thoſe who truly believe in him, even Jeſus Chriſt our only Lord and Saviour.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:174612:65"/>
               <head>Meditations after Recovery.</head>
               <div n="Pſal" type="part">
                  <head>Pſal. 116.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. I Am well pleaſed, that the Lord hath heard the voice of my Prayer.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That he hath enclined his Ear unto me: therefore will I call upon him as long as I live.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Snares of Death compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me round about; and the Pains of Hell got hold upon me.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I ſhall find trouble and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs, and I ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord: O Lord, I beſeech thee deliver my Soul.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Gracious is the Lord &amp; Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; yea, our God is merciful.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Lord preſerveth the Simple: I was in miſery, and he helped me.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Turn again then unto thy reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord hath rewarded thee.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:174612:65"/>8. And why? thou haſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered my Soul from Death, mine Eyes from Tears, and my Feet from falling.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. I will walk before the Lord in the Land of the Living.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. I believed, and therefore will I ſpeak, but I was ſore troubled: I ſaid in my haſt, all Men are Lyars.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. What reward ſhall I give unto the Lord, for all the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits that he hath done unto me?</p>
                  <p n="12">12. I will receive the Cup of Salvation, and call upon the Name of the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. I will pay my Vows now in the preſence of all his People: right dear in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Behold (O Lord) how that I am thy Servant. I am thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and the Son of thine Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid; thou haſt broken my Bonds in ſunder.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. I will offer to thee the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Thankſgiving; and will
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:174612:66"/> call upon the Name of the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. I will pay my Vows unto the Lord in the ſight of all his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; in the Courts of the Lord's Houſe, even in the midſt of thee, O Jeruſalem. Praiſe the Lord.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving after Recovery.</head>
               <p>O Holy and immortal God, I Laud and Praiſe thy holy Name that thou haſt been pleaſed to deliver me from the Jaws of Death, and the Pit of Corruption; and in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure reſtored me again to my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Health, crowning me with thy mercy and loving kindneſs, my Soul, and all that is within me, ſhall magnifie thee; I will praiſe thee, O Lord, with my whole Heart, and will extol
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:174612:66"/> thee, O thou that dwelleſt in the Heavens.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>It is thou alone that haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved my life from deſtruction; thou didſt caſt me down upon my Bed of Sickneſs, and haſt raiſed me up again by thy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power; thou haſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened and corrected me, but not given me over unto Death. My time is in thy hand, O God, thou art the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh; grant that this remnant of Life, that thou haſt thus graciouſly ſpared, may be wholly dedicated to thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that I may walk before thee in newneſs and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>O thou that art the only Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian of Soul and Body, thou haſt once more permitted me to take
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:174612:67"/> up my Bed and walk; O make me ſtrictly careful, as the wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Night, to be vigilant over all my Thoughts, Words, and Actions, that I may ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing happen unto me. Let not this great mercy thou haſt now given me, make me ſupine and negligent, and entertain thoſe Thoughts that my Lord delayeth his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; but grant, I beſeech thee, that I may make a right uſe of this thy Fatherly Chaſtiſement, and employ the remainder of my Life to thy Glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>I have found by experience of thine afflicting hand, what a dreadful thing it is to be ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away by the hands of Death, without our accompts, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared; O let it be a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al admonition to me, to ſtand
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:174612:67"/> upon my Guard, and to watch for my Maſter's coming; and whenever the Pleaſures of Sin, which endure but for a Seaſon, ſhall preſent themſelves to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and allure me, make me to remember the bitterneſs of them at laſt. Lord, hear me, and grant me grace to work out my own Salvation, for thy dear Son's ſake.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer fit to be ſaid at any time.</head>
               <p>O Moſt glorious and powerful Lord God, who createdſt all things out of nothing, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port'ſt the whole Univerſe by thy Providence; I confeſs, O Lord, I was conceived in Original Sin, now full of actual tranſgreſſions; I was in the Womb a loathſome Subſtance; I am in the World a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:174612:68"/> Lump of Corruption; and I ſhall be in the Grave a prey for Vermin.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>But, I know (bleſſed Jeſus) thy Grace is ſufficient for me; thy Mercy can expreſs it ſelf in my Miſery. I know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs (O Lord) that my Sins are exceeding many, mighty, and heinous, yet thy Mercy is far greater; for thou art infinite in mercy, but I cannot be infinite in ſinning; and the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt Jeſus the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is more prevalent for me than my own Unrighteouſneſs can be againſt my ſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>The Fountain of thy Mercy (O God) hath quenched the fire of thy Juſtice, and graceleſs Man falling from Goodneſs, is by thee repoſſeſſed of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:174612:68"/> Wherefore I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, O Lord, give me the Grace of continual Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, ſtrengthen my Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, correct my Sinfulneſs, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my future Frailty, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me againſt the Adverſary, kindle my Zeal, enlighten my Underſtanding, ſoften my ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Heart, and ſave for ever my immortal Soul.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>And though my whole Life, O Lord, hath been impure and undefiled in thy ſight, yet through thy precious Blood and Paſſion, by thine all-ſufficient Sacrifice, Obligation, and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, revert my deſerved Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and convert my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Evils, to preſent good and future joys, in thine eternal and moſt glorious Kingdom.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:174612:69"/>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Pardon, good Lord, my loſs of Time, my abuſe of thy good Creatures, my negligence in my lawful Employment, my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſs for thy Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs; and whatſoever is wanting in my Perſon, Practice, Prayer, or Thankſgiving, make a ſupply of it in the Merits of thy Son <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> to whom with thee, and thy bleſſed <hi>Spirit,</hi> be all Praiſe and Glory, now and evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Prayers for all Perſons and Occaſions.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Church.</head>
               <p>ALmighty and everlaſting God, who haſt revealed thy Glory both to <hi>Jews</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:174612:69"/> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, extend thy hand of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Mercy over all the World, that thy Church may ſpread like a flouriſhing Vine, and enlarge her Borders to the uttermoſt Parts of the Earth, that all Nations partaking of the ſweet refreſhments of thy Goſpel, thy Name may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, the honour of our Lord Jeſus advanced, his Prophecies fulfilled, and his Coming haſtned.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs, O Lord, thy holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Apoſtolick Church with all Bleſſings of Comfort, Aſſiſtance, and Preſervation; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate Hereſies, unite her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, give her Patience and Perſeverance in the Faith, and Confeſſion of thy Name in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of all Enmities, Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Diſadvantages; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:174612:70"/> all wicked Counſels inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or levied againſt her or any of her Children, by the Devil or any of his accurſed Inſtruments; let the hands of thy Grace and Mercy lead her from this Vale of Miſery to the triumphant Throne of her Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the King.</head>
               <p>WE beſeech thee, O Lord, to bleſs and preſerve thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>William</hi> our moſt gracious King and Governour, with the richeſt Bleſſings of thy Grace and Favour; make him valiant and proſperous as King <hi>David,</hi> wiſe and rich like <hi>Solomon,</hi> be unto him a Helmet of Salvation againſt the Face of his Enemies, and a ſtrong Tower of Defence in the Time of Adverſity; as for
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:174612:70"/> his Enemies, let them be cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Shame, but upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf let his Crown for ever flouriſh. Grant him a long and a proſperous Reign; let Peace and Unity, Holineſs, and Juſtice, Truth, and all Chriſtian Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues flouriſh in his time. Let all his Subjects faithfully ſerve him with Honour and due O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; and let him ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve thee his God, here on Earth, that he may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after everlaſtingly reign with thee in Heaven, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Royal Family.</head>
               <p>O God, the Father of all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, bleſs and preſerve <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> the Queen Dowager,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:174612:71"/> the Princeſs <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> with all the reſt of the Royal Family; unite them unto thee with the Bands of Faith and Love, preſerve them to their Lives end in thy Favour, make them Inſtruments of Glory to thy Name, of refreſhment to the Church, of joy to all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful People of this Kingdom; proſper them with all Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs here on Earth, and crown them at laſt with an Eternal Weight of Glory, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for our Parents.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God, who from the Loins of our Firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> didſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Mankind, and haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to Honour and Obey our Parents, in purſuance of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:174612:71"/> thy holy Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of our Duty to thee our God, and in thee to them, we do with all humility beg a Bleſſing of thee for our Parents, who from thy Mercy and Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have conveyed many to us; pardon and forgive all their Sins and Infirmities, encreaſe in them all Goodneſs, give them Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Right Hand, and Bleſſings of the Left, bleſs them in their Perſons and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, in their Goods and good Name, in the Comforts of thy Holy Spirit, in a perſevering Goodneſs, and at laſt in an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Weight of Glory, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:174612:72"/>
               <head>A Prayer of Parents for their Children.</head>
               <p>O God, the Creator of all the World, by whoſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence Mankind is propagated; I bleſs thy holy Name for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing on me the Bleſſing of Children. Lord, bleſs them with Life and Health, with good Underſtanding, fair Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, and Advantages of good Education; but above all, with the Gifts and Graces of thy Holy Spirit, that they may live and be bleſſed under thy Protection, grow in Grace, and be in favour with God and Man, and at laſt may make up the number of thine Elect Children, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:174612:72"/>
               <head>A Prayer for our Friends and Benefactors.</head>
               <p>O Thou Fountain of all Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, from whom proceeds all Excellency both to Men and Angels, extend thy favour and loving-kindneſs to all my Friends and Benefactors: Reward them and make them plentiful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation for all the Benefits which from thy merciful Hand of Providence they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to me. Let the Light of thy Countenance ſo ſhine upon them as they may never enter into any Deſolation or Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſuch as may be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to thy Glory, and their Eternal Comfort, through our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:174612:73"/>
               <head>A Prayer of a Wife for her Husband.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed Lord, who haſt been graciouſly pleaſed to call me to the holy State of Matrimony, bleſs me in it with the Grace of Chaſtity, Loyalty, Obedience, and a dutiful Complacency to my Husband. Bleſs him with a long Life, a healthful Body, and an underſtanding Heart, and furniſh him with all thoſe Gifts and Graces which may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to be and continue thy Servant, that he may be a Supporter and a Guide to me his Wife, a Bleſſing and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to his Children, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:174612:73"/>
               <head>A Prayer of a Husband for his Wife.</head>
               <p>O Moſt gracious God, who art a Father to us thy Children, a Spouſe to thy holy Church, a Saviour and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to all Mankind; have Mercy upon thy Handmaid my Wife, endue her with all the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thy heavenly Grace; make her to be as Religious as <hi>Heſter,</hi> Loving as <hi>Rachel,</hi> Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as <hi>Leah,</hi> Wiſe as <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and Obedient as <hi>Sarah,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with Grace and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction here, ſhe may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of thy Glory hereafter, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer of an Orphan.</head>
               <p>O God gracious and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who art ready to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:174612:74"/> all thoſe that are diſtreſſed, and haſt promiſed to be a Father to the Fatherleſs. Have Mercy upon me, O Lord, I humbly beſeech thee, who am left a poor Orphan, and by thy heavenly will and pleaſure deprived of my earthly Parents: Supply, O Lord, all my Wants and Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, guide, govern and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me with thy good Spirit, that in all my Words, Works and Actions, I may glorifie thee my heavenly Father. Let thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Grace ſuſtain me, and work in me Obedience to my Superiors, and thoſe which have the charge and care over me; that they diſcharging a good Conſcience towards me, I may by thy ready help improve my time, to the Praiſe and Glory of thy holy Name, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:174612:74"/>
               <head>The Widow's Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Moſt holy Lord God, the Comforter of all thoſe who are in any affliction, ſorrow or trouble The Bands of Death, by thy appointment, have made a ſeparation between me and him whom thou gaveſt to be my Husband, who was my Head and ſupreme Governour, and the only Guide I had in this World next under thee. Grant me grace to bear this croſs and loſs patiently, and to put my whole Truſt and Confidence in thee; let thy tender Care go along with me, in preſerving me from all Oppreſſion and Wrong, and deliver me from the Hands of thoſe who will devour Widows Houſes. Bleſs me, O Lord, as thou didſt the poor Widow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> let not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:174612:75"/> the Barrel of Meal waſt, but grant me a competency fit for my Eſtate, neither let the Cruiſe of Oil fail, but aſſiſt me with thy Grace, that I may walk worthily towards thee, and all the World. Let my continual Prayers and Supplications a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend up to thee; and hear, O Lord, and have mercy when I cry unto thee, for the alone ſake of thy dear Son, my only Saviour and Redeemer.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Servant's Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Moſt mighty God, and the great Lord and Maſter of all the World, who beholdeſt with thine all-ſeeing Eye thy great Houſhold and Family here on Earth; look upon me thine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Servant, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, with thine Eye of Providence; grant me a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:174612:75"/> Mind in that ſtate thou haſt placed me in, ſo ſhall I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a continual Feaſt: Aſſiſt me, O Lord, with thy heavenly Grace, that I may perform O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and be ſubject to my earthly Maſters, whom thou haſt been pleaſed to ſet over me whether they be Good or Evil, Courteous or Froward. Proſper all the Deſigns I ſhall take in hand, in this my Servitude, which are not in oppoſition to thy Commands: Preſerve and keep me from all Evil, that no Enticements may allure me ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to embezel away any thing committed to my Cuſtody, or have Society with ſuch who are Enemies to my Maſter's Houſe: let me chearfully proceed in my Service, that the Glaſs of my Time may run out with Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and I in the end ſhall be
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:174612:76"/> made Free of that City of thine, the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> where I may reſt for evermore.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Maid's Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Holy Lord God, let thine Handmaid ſpeak in thine Audience, and hearken unto her when ſhe calleth upon thee, though I know not how to ask aright, yet teach me the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thee, and how to beg thoſe things that are requiſite and neceſſary for me: Inlighten my Soul with thy divine Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that I may ſee and do thoſe things that appertain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Godlineſs. Let me keep my honeſt Reputation in the Eye of the World, knowing that a <hi>good Name</hi> is better than <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Ointment:</hi> But, eſpecially in thy ſight, let me be pure, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and undefiled, ſo ſhall I
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:174612:76"/> not be aſhamed in the great Day of Account. Defend me from Sin, Satan, and the Poiſon of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Tongues; aſſiſt me with thy directing hand, that the labours which this day I am to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take may proſper; grant me Grace to love, honour and ſerve thee in Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all my days, that I may glorifie thy holy Name, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for one afflicted in Mind.</head>
               <p>O Eternal Lord God, who art fearful in Praiſes, doing Wonders, I tremble, and am even at Death's Door; for alas! I am the vileſt of all Sinners, my Conſcience is ſo clogged with Evil, that I cannot look up; my Wickedneſſes have gone o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my Head, and are as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:174612:77"/> too heavy for me to bear; my Spirit is ſorrowful, my Heart is heavy, my words are ſtopp'd with Sighs, and my Plaints wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with Tears: O Lord, what ſhall I deſire of thee, that deſerve nothing at thy Hand? What can I hope for, that am even hopeleſs? My Conſcience is reſtleſs, and my Ungodlineſs fettereth me: and even all my unrighteous Actions cry out for Vengeance againſt me; my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is overwhelmed and weary of this Bondage, and I have bid my life farewell.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>O but let thy Majeſty (O Lord) yet appear in thy Mercy; forgive my Sin, the unhappy ground of all this woe: Where my miſery hath thus abounded, there let thy Mercy much more abound. I dare not add this
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:174612:77"/> grievous Sin unto my other Sins to deſpair of thy Mercy: What were more Sacrilegious? for thou art a skilful Phyſician and canſt cure all my Infirmities; thou art a merciful God, and canſt forgive all my Sins: To thee do I fly for refuge which art the Land of Safety, to thee do I lift up my Hands and my Heart, and to thee do I pray, deſiring thy Mercy. Let the power of thy Son's Death and Paſſion defeat all the Devices of the Devil againſt me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Inſtruct me in thy heavenly Wiſdom, lead me in thy Truth in this dangerous Sea of Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and Affliction: keep me from ſhipwrack, and bring me ſafe to the Land of Peace-Strengthen my Faith, ſanctifie all thoſe good means unto me
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:174612:78"/> wherein I ſeek relief, as Prayer, Conference, Reading, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy holy Word. Mitigate my Perplexities, grant me Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, heal my Imperfections: Thou that wilt not break a bruiſed Reed, ſpare and have Mercy upon me: Thou that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt not in the death of a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, receive me. Though my Heart condemns me, yet do thou releaſe me. O Lord hear, O Lord forgive, O Lord defer not, but even now ſpeak peace unto me: ſay unto my Soul, I am thy Salvation; to whom be aſcribed all Honour and Glory World without end.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving, for God's ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son to ſave Mankind.</head>
               <p>O Almighty and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lord God, we might utterly deſpair, and be caſt
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:174612:78"/> down, conſidering our manifold Sins and infinite Offences, had not thy Word been made Fleſh, and dwelt among us; but now we dare not deſpair, for if, when we were Enemies, we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto thee by the Death of thy Son; how much more, being reconciled, are we ſaved by his Life? All our hope, and all our confidence is repoſed in that precious Blood which was ſhed for us, and for our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>O how greatly are we wretches bound to fear thee, to love thee, to bleſs and praiſe thee, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee, and to glorifie thee, ſeeing we are redeemed at ſuch a price, ſaved with ſuch a gift, cheriſhed with ſo many promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and bleſſings of the ſame, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thy Son our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:174612:79"/> Chriſt! Stabliſh, O God, that which thou haſt wrought in us; finiſh what thou haſt begun, that we may be able to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fulneſs of thy Mercy; make us through thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to underſtand, and through thy Son to diſcern, and with due honour and reverence, this high Myſtery of Godlineſs, which is, how <hi>God was manifeſt in the Fleſh, juſtified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, believed on in the World, and received up into Glory;</hi> where we doubt not but we ſhall Reign with him for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Prayer of a Woman with Child.</head>
               <p>O God, the Creator and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of all Mankind, Comforter of all that call upon
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:174612:79"/> thee, and the only deliverer of ſuch as are in danger; be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, I beſeech thee, and look down in mercy from thy throne upon me thine Handmaid, and upon the Fruit of my Womb; behold, I ſeek and ſue unto thee for a Bleſſing at this time; my Sin is great, my Danger at hand not ſmall; my Pains to come will be grievous, and my Life is now moſt uncertain.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Aſſure me, I beſeech thee, of the forgiveneſs of all my Sins, mitigate my Fear, and aſſwage my Sorrows, ſtrengthen me with the refreſhing of thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, confirm me in the Faith of my Saviour, and bleſs all good means appointed for my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that in due time I may be a joyful Mother, and ſee the Fruit of my Body, ſafe, ſound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="156" facs="tcp:174612:80"/> and perfect, without blemiſh or deformity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>O Lord, I know not how ſoon my Travail will overtake me, when I muſt encounter with Life or Death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one drop of thy Mercy hath ſovereign power to cure all the Wounds of thoſe Sorrows: Shed therefore (O holy Father) that drop of Grace upon me in that minute, when I am to encounter with ſo ſtern an Adverſary: Strengthen me with Patience, preſerve me that I periſh not, and bleſs the work of my Midwife.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Let not the Child yet unborn, the Babe in my Womb, be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for mine Offences, but give it growth, form, and what thou ſeeſt in thy good pleaſure to be fit and neceſſary for it;
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:174612:80"/> and when the time is come that thou wilt call it out of this cloſe houſe of fleſh, where it now inhabiteth, to dwell in the open World, ſanctifie thy Creature; make it by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> a Member of thy Church, a Lamb of thy Flock, and direct it in the ways of thy Commandments to its Life's End.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Midwife's Prayer.</head>
               <p>MOſt gracious God, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone haſt the power to produce Children from the Womb and bring them into the light of this World I thy moſt unworthy Servant, whom thou haſt appointed for this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to be a help and comfort to all thoſe which are in Extremity and near the time of their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, do in all humility pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:174612:81"/> my ſelf before thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thee to vouchſafe me thy divine Aſſiſtance in theſe Performances.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Have Mercy upon me and bleſs me, guide me and govern me in all my Actions, proſper all my Undertakings, grant that I may be as careful of the Poor as of the Rich, that I may do good and not hurt, ſave Life and not deſtroy it by my negligence; help my Infirmities and Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that I may neither be too timorious nor too raſh in the performance of my Duty, but grant me art and judgment in the happy finiſhing all my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Work in me an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and a tender Heart, and whatſoever elſe is neceſſary in
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:174612:81"/> my undertakings; and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully grant, O Lord, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever my Duty calls me either by Night, or Day, I may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways prepared; preſerve and defend me from the infection of all contagious Diſeaſes; by thy moſt gracious Favour grant me a proſperous ſucceſs, that whatſoever I do may tend to thy Glory, the comfort and help of all good Women (committed to my charge) and my own cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer to be ſaid by thoſe that are preſent with a Woman in Travail.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, we are here aſſembled for the comfort of this Woman, who travaileth in pain to be delivered of a Child. Through the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:174612:82"/> of our firſt Parents, ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be delivered but with great ſorrow; for thou haſt laid thine heavy diſpleaſure upon us ſinful Women, that in <hi>much ſorrow ſhall we bring forth Children;</hi> yet ſince thou haſt given us Faith in thy Son, give us all (eſpecially to this Woman thy Servant now in this Extremity) patience; mitigate her Pains, proſper our Work, bleſs our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, that by our help ſhe may be delivered, and forget her pains, <hi>becauſe a Child is born into the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>We pray unto thee for this Child in her Womb; thou haſt inrolled it in thy Book, thou haſt made it in thy Frame, the Bones thereof are not hid from thee, all the Members of it are written in thy Volume. Thou didſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:174612:82"/> it at the time of Life, viſit it now at the hour of Birth, that thou maiſt receive glory by thy works and the Mother glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in beholding her Infant, after all her Sorrows. Give her, we beſeech thee, neither a monſtrous, a maimed, nor a dead Birth; but as thou haſt bleſſed the Conception of this Infant, ſo bring it with Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction into the World. Hear us, O Lord, and help this thy weak Servant, viſit her as thou didſt <hi>Sarah,</hi> comfort her as thou didſt <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and chear her as thou didſt <hi>Leah;</hi> forgive her all her ſins, and whether ſhe be ſure to live or die, let her truſt in thee, and let thine Angels pitch their Tents about her, now and for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:174612:83"/>
               <head>A Thanksgiving by thoſe that are preſent after Delivery.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, infinite in Mercies towards all thy Sons and Daughters in affliction; we deſire to praiſe and magnifie thy holy Name, acknowledging thy Goodneſs to us, and thy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial favour to this Woman thy Servant. We called upon thee, and thou heard'ſt us; we peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for thy Favour to thine Hand-maid, and thou regardedſt her; we begg'd a Bleſſing for her Child, thou haſt bleſſed it, and haſt made her a joyful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. We offer unto thee the Sacrifice of our Lips; let our thankfulneſs aſcend up unto thee like a ſweet-ſmelling ſavour.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Continue thy loving kindneſs to this thy Servant, keep her
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:174612:83"/> from all further peril and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Child-Bed; give her ſtrength to recover her weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, joy to forget her late ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and thankfulneſs that ſuch a Child is come out of her Loins, as one day ſhall inherit the Kingdom of Heaven. Give thy Bleſſing to the Infant now born that it may in due time increaſe in Wiſdom, Stature, and Favour with God and Man. Baptize i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with <hi>Water</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> endue it with all heavenly Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, defend it againſt all Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, provide for it in this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Life, and crown it in the end with Life everlaſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs us, O Lord, that are here met together to behold the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Creation, and the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our Creator in this little Infant: Let us in all Sobriety,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:174612:84"/> Chaſtity, and Godlineſs, walk before thee all the Days of our Lives. Make us like <hi>fruitful Vines,</hi> and our Children like <hi>Olive Branches round about our Tables:</hi> Let our Husbands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in us, and make us careful to love them, as thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us, that thy Kingdom may be increaſed, the Bed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt glorified, to whom be praiſe for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving by the Woman after Delivery.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed Lord God, I yield thee all Honour, Glory, and Praiſe, who haſt now delivered me from the great pain and peril of Child-Birth, who haſt taken away my reproach, and made me an Inſtrument to encreaſe thy Kingdom. It is in thy power
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:174612:84"/> to ſtrike death into my womb, but thou haſt given me a double life; all mine anguiſhes thou haſt ſweetened with gladneſs. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thy Mercies and Favours to me thy Servant, that my lips may render thee hearty thanks.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Look upon this my Infant which thou haſt given me; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it in Health, quicken it with Grace, crown it with long Life, that it may grow up to be a Servant in thine houſhold. Send the Father of it and me much Comfort by it, that it may be a Staff to our Old Age: Bleſs it with ſtore of Friends in this World, and be thou a chief Friend to it for evermore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>And for the better growth in Grace, feed it with the Milk of thy holy Word, defend it from
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:174612:85"/> all dangers ghoſtly and bodily: Guard me, and regard this my Birth, that Satan rule not nor reign within us, but deliver us ſtill out of his Jaws as a <hi>Bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler;</hi> let thy bleſſing, O Lord, be upon me and my Children, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more keep and defend us.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving after a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from any Calamity.</head>
               <p>ALmighty and everlaſting God, who haſt ſuffered thy Church ſo to be tempted with Afflictions, that it is never free either from the Sword of <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> which is a reviling tongue, or the Sword of <hi>Eſau,</hi> a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hand, having taught us all to drink of the ſame Cup our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter did; ſo ſtrengthen me with Patience, direct me by thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:174612:85"/> and uphold me by Faith, that all trouble may be as wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to my Soul, as afflicted <hi>Ruth</hi> was to the Field of <hi>Boaz.</hi> Though troubles are many and increaſe daily, yet thou, O Lord, knoweſt how to deliver us out of all: <hi>Heavineſs may endure for a Night, but joy will come in the Morning:</hi> Doubtleſs there is a Reward for the Righteous, and a Rod for the Wicked. Let one Plague follow another as one Quail ſings to another; yet as the Viper leaped on St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Hand, and immediately leaped off again, ſo one trouble ſhall leap upon the Righteous, and in an Inſtant ſhall as ſoon vaniſh; though he fall he ſhall riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; for the righteous ſhall not be forſaken for ever.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>I have lately taſted of thy
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:174612:86"/> goodneſs, O Lord, I have now been ſenſible of thy Mercy in a great Meaſure by this great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance. I have had experience many times of thy loving-kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but never more than in thy late Favours. I chattered like a <hi>Swallow,</hi> I mourned like a <hi>Dove,</hi> I panted like a <hi>Hart,</hi> but thou haſt put life again into my Soul; thou haſt not dealt with me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Sins, nor reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me according to mine Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: As high as the Heaven is above the Earth, ſo great is thy Mercy towards them that fear thee; ſince thy Mercy, O Lord, hath been ſo great towards me; grant that I may love thee more zealouſly, fear thee more reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and obey thee more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully all the days of my Life. For as <hi>Elkanah</hi> was to <hi>Hannah</hi> inſtead of many Sons, ſo be thou
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:174612:86"/> ſtill to me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, inſtead of many Comforters. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve me therefore patience in trouble, a conſtancy in hope, rooted and grounded in love; and ſo bring me, O Lord, from this valley of tears to life everlaſting.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before taking of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or any outward means for reſtoring of Health.</head>
               <p>MOſt mighty God, the great Phyſician both of Soul and Body, who by thy bleſſing on a lump of dry figgs didſt heal <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi>'s Boil, that he recovered; and by laying thy hand upon the head of <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Wife's Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> didſt cure her of her Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and anointing the Eyes with Clay and Spittle, didſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Man that was blind e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from his Birth unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Sight, and by ſeven times
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:174612:87"/> waſhing in the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> didſt cleanſe <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> of his Leproſie; and by thine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment haſt provided means for thy Children, for the curing of their Sickneſs, and recovery of their Health.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>I dare not, O Lord, without injury to my Soul, and indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to thine Omnipotency, deſpair of thy ſufficiency and power for the reſtoring me to health, or not uſe that help, and expect a bleſſing upon thoſe means which are requiſite I ſhould chooſe and uſe for the repairing of my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the reſtitution of my Strength. I dare not ſend unto Sorcerers, Wizards, Charmers, or Inchanters for help; nor with <hi>Ahaziah</hi> go to <hi>Baalzebub,</hi> the God of <hi>Ekron,</hi> for relief, and leave thee the God of <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:174612:87"/> But I renounce and reject all other help but from thee alone; and upon the bended knees of an humble heart I come unto thee, beſeeching thee to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie what I am now to receive or apply to my eaſe and good, and to give ſuch a bleſſing thereunto, that it may remove ſuch pain &amp; ſickneſs as doth afflict my Body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>O Lord, grant me in all my Sickneſs, patience, and not to murmur or repine at thy affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting hand: and in health give me a provident care to prevent all ſuch maladies, as by reaſon of my manifold Sins thou maiſt juſtly inflict upon me. And as <hi>David</hi>'s Troubles made him pray, <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Sickneſs to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Prodigal</hi> return home, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> under <hi>Aegypt</hi>'s bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens cry unto thee, ſo I beſeech
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:174612:88"/> thee, that every Chaſtiſement of thine may compel me the rather to ſue unto thee for thy ſaving Health, Pity, Compaſſion and Grace: And as Chriſt told his Diſciples, that <hi>Lazarus's ſickneſs was not unto Death, but for the glory of God,</hi> ſo I beſeech thee that none of my afflictions may be unto the death of my Soul, but rather for the good both of Body and Soul. And as <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark, the higher it was toſſed with the <hi>Flood,</hi> the nearer it mounted towards Heaven, ſo my Soul being ſanctified by Grace, the more it is exerciſed with the water of affliction, the nearer let it be lifted up towards thee, O God; grant this, O holy Father, for thy dear Son's ſake, to whom with Thee and the Holy Ghoſt be all honour and glory, both now and evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:174612:88"/>
               <head>A Prayer before a Journey or Voyage.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God, who preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thy Servants in all their ways, and didſt protect and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect <hi>Jacob</hi> in his way to <hi>Laban, Jonah</hi> in his Voyage, and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Travels over <hi>Jordan:</hi> Guide me thine unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in the Journey that I am now to undertake: Lord, walk with me, be about my Bed, and about my Paths; keep me from all dangers both of Body &amp; Soul, refreſh me when I am weary, comfort me when I am ſolitary, and ſend me health and ſtrength of Body to perform it. Deliver me from Thieves, Robbers, and ſavage Beaſts; furniſh me with all neceſſaries, and ſend me home again in ſafety.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:174612:89"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Send me, I beſeech thee, good ſucceſs in all my undertakings; and grant that I may undertake nothing but what ſhall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in thy ſight. If I meet with Company, grant they may be ſuch as I may receive good by, rather than harm; if I am alone, let thy Law be my delight; grant that I may then meditate ſuch things as ſhall be for the benefit and ſalvation of my Soul; and grant that after my buſineſs is fully accompliſhed, when I return home, I may find my Friends, Wife, Children and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in perfect Health; and though my whole Life be but a continual Travel here, yet ſend me everlaſting peace, with thee and thy Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:174612:89"/>
               <head>A Prayer upon return from a Journey or Voyage.</head>
               <p>MOſt merciful and gracious Lord God, keeper of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> the well-ſpring of Life, and the alone preſerver of all Mankind; I render unto thee all hearty Thanks and Praiſe for thy provident care, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous protection of me in this my Journey, whereas I might have periſhed, e're I had ſeen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain this my Habitation; but that thou haſt walked before me, <hi>by day as a pillar of a Cloud</hi> to guide me in the way, and by <hi>night in a pillar of Fire</hi> to give me light. Thou directeſt me in all my paths, O lead me into the way of Life.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Give me an humble and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heart; let me not bury this
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:174612:90"/> and other thy Favours in forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; but let my Soul ſtill praiſe thee; and thy good Spirit lead me into the Land of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. As thou haſt brought me, O Lord, through this Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Voyage, and kept this Tabernacle of my Body unſplit: So in thy good time bring my Soul home to the Land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, the Everlaſting Haven of eternal Reſt, and that for thy Son's ſake, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Mariner's Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, who rebukeſt the Winds, and ſtilleſt the raging of the Sea, and the noiſe of the Tempeſt, whoſe way is in the Waters, and thy wonders in the Deep, we are in danger every moment of periſhing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by thy miraculous Power thou deliver us from death, when
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:174612:90"/> with thy Servant <hi>Peter</hi> we cry out, <hi>Help, Lord, we periſh;</hi> let thy hand be ſtretched forth to command the Waters to be ſtill. Fill our Sails with gentle and alſo proſperous Gales; ſave us from Shipwrack, defend us from Pyrates and Robbers, preſerve us from Lightning, Tempeſt, and Captivity; hold the Winds in thy right hand, and the Waves in thy left, keep us from Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe fearful Crack may rend us in pieces; ſave us in the bitterneſs of Froſt, Hail, Ice, Snow, or Whirlwind; let us be prepared for Death, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate upon thoſe things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern our better Life.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Send us the Prayers of thoſe that are upon Land, and bleſs all our Friends that are now parted from us. Save our Souls
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:174612:91"/> from the great <hi>Leviathan</hi> whoſe Jaws are ready to devour us. Make good our Proviſion for Bodily Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance, as well as Furniture for our Ships. Let thy Peace be amongſt us; ſave us, ſuccour, and defend us, O Lord, thou Anchor of our Hope, for thy Glory, and for thy Name's ſake, to whom be Praiſe and Glory, World without end.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving for a ſafe arrival upon the Land after a Storm.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, who haſt now delivered me out of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the raging Sea, and brought me to a Port of reſt; O make me truly thankful unto thee for this thy favour and mercy, and in thy due time lead me alſo from out of the troubleſome Sea of this World, unto the longed for Haven, and eternal Bliſs and Happineſs. Thou haſt brought me out of a great deal of danger, which I was liable to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:174612:91"/> whilſt I was amongſt the boiſterous Waves and foaming Billows of the Waters. I am ſubject, O Lord every hour to as many Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils being now at Land, how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſo ever I may think my ſelf to be; my feet are ſtill ſlipping into the Grave, I beſeech thee to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me; to ſave, preſerve and keep me, that I may ſtill glorifie thee, the God of my Salvation.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Give me Wiſdom, Sobriety, and Temperance when I now come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my old Lovers &amp; Friends; Cauſe me to make a right uſe of thoſe things which I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and beheld in Foreign Parts; free my Soul and Conſcience from any ſtain of Corruption and Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which may hurt or deſtroy me; keep me in all my ways; ſend me Health, and all things neceſſary for this Life, that having paſſed the Waves of this troubleſome World I may at laſt ſafely arrive at the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:174612:92"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="179" facs="tcp:174612:92"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="180" facs="tcp:174612:93"/> harbour of everlaſting reſt, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for Rain.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed Lord, who commandeſt the former and the latter Rain; who in the time of <hi>Elias</hi> didſt ſo ſhut up the Flood-gates of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that <hi>it rained not on the Earth for the ſpace of Three Years and ſix Months;</hi> and yet when he prayed, the Heaven gave Rain, and the Earth brought forth her Fruit; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold us thy People, who mourn for want of moiſture; the Rivers of Waters are dried up and the Trees of the Field are withered: ſend now, we beſeech thee, a gracious Rain upon thine Inheritance, and refreſh it now it is weary; make the Springs as Milk to moiſten and to water the Valleys, ſo ſhall the Earth bring forth her increaſe; our Land have a plentiful ſupply, and our Garners be furniſhed with ſtore: our Baskets ſhall be repleniſhed,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:174612:93"/> our Cattle increaſed, and thy holy Name for ever magnified.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>We do confeſs and acknowledge, O Lord, that our Sins call for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death and deſtruction; and conſidering our deſervings, we cannot expect any bleſſing at thy hands. Pardon, we beſeech thee, what is paſt; give us Obedience and Grace to do thy Will for the time to come, and to ſatisfie the lawful deſires of us thy Servants, that we may not be wanting of our Food and daily Bread, but may be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtakers of thy heavenly Bleſſings, and wait upon thee for our Meat in due ſeaſon. Oppreſs us not with too much Poverty, O Lord, neither puff us up with too much Plenty, but give us a competent ſtore of things neceſſary for this life, and grace to uſe them ſoberly to thy glory and our comfort, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:174612:94"/>
               <head>A Prayer for fair Weather.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, who feedeſt with thy bleſſing every living thing, and ſatisfieſt the lawful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of thy Servants, with thy bountiful Goodneſs, we wretched Sinners, unworthy of the leaſt of thy Benefits, humbly beſeech thee, that thine Anger may ceaſe which is threatned againſt us, by this <hi>Rain</hi> and <hi>Tempeſt.</hi> Defend us from thoſe Evils which we are now likely to ſuffer: make our Habitations like the Land of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> in the times of the Plagues of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Cauſe not the Waters, O God, thus to ſwell; let not thy thunder go forth againſt us.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Preſerve our Bodies, Houſes, and Goods; keep us from Deluge and Inundation, and ſhew us ſome ſpeedy token of Peace: Send us a Remedy in this our preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt miſery; turn our Dearth into Cheapneſs,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:174612:94"/> and our Scarcity into Plenty. Give a bleſſing to that which we ſhall reap; bleſs our ſtore; furniſh us wherewithal to relieve others; let not thy hand be ſhortned at this time, but rebuke the Wind and Storm, that we may have a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Calm.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>At thy Word, O Lord, the <hi>Mountains</hi> ſmoak, the <hi>Heavens</hi> tremble, and the <hi>Earth</hi> quakes; at thine Anger the <hi>Sea</hi> roareth, and makes a noiſe, and the fearful <hi>Depths</hi> are broken down and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; thou commandeſt the Clouds and they obey: O ſhut them up for a time, and let thy puniſhing Angel be no more ſeen. Hear us, O Lord, in theſe our Prayers, that with joyful and thankful Hearts, we may ſing Praiſes unto thee, who ruleſt all things, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:174612:95"/>
               <head>A Prayer of a Child before he goes to School.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God, who has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, that out of the mouths of Babes and Sucklings, thou wilt have thy Wonders expreſſed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am a Child, and cannot ſpeak unto thee, or call upon thee as I ſhould; but open thou my Lips, that my Mouth may ſhew forth thy Praiſe: Pour into my Lips the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Well of Life, that I may learn thoſe things that may lead me unto the knowledge of thy holy Laws.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Let me remember thee, my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, in the days of my youth, while the evil days come not. Teach me, O Lord, how to lead my life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of Godlineſs. Make me obedient to my Parents, dutiful to my Teachers, proud to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards no man, but rightly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned towards all People. Add un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me length of Days, ſupply me
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:174612:95"/> with vertues, guide my feet in thy ways, direct my mind, ſanctifie my ſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies, govern all my actions, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my Body in health, my Soul from uncleanneſs; take from me all dulneſs and incapacity, that may hinder my growth in knowledge, and bring me to life everlaſting, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> my only Lord and Saviour.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer in time of War.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, who ruleſt and beholdeſt all the World, and haſt many times miraculouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved &amp; defended us; we beſeech thee to ſhew thy power in theſe needful and perillous times, whilſt there is nothing but Wars, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of Wars amongſt us. Save us, O Lord our God, from our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and put them to ſhame that hate us, turn the weapons of our Adverſaries and their Accomplices into their own Boſoms. Bleſs thoſe that are abroad for the defence of
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:174612:96"/> our Country; and ſanctifie us at home to pleaſe thee, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they or we do, it may proſper.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Be preſent and preſident amongſt us in all our Conſultations; ſend us wiſe Counſellors and Commanders, who may prudently foreſee, and valiantly defeat the devices and ſtratagems of their Enemies. Bleſs thoſe that are prepared to fight for us; command the Winds and the Seas to favour them, and let the Land ſpeak peace unto them. Let neither the Sun nor Moon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy them, nor alteration of diet or place diſable them; anoint their Shields, hallow and conſecrate all their Engines of War, with happy ſucceſs to do thy will.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Refreſh both Prince and People with the ſweet ſavour and harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Peace, rather than the bitter howlings &amp; clamours of War, that we may every one in our due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:174612:96"/> ſit under our own Vine, and under our own Fig-tree, that there may be no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eading into Captivity, nor no complaining in our Streets; grant, O Lord, theſe things we have begged, for thy Son, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's ſake.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving after Victory.</head>
               <p>VVE praiſe and bleſs thy holy Name, O Lord, that thou haſt ſaved us from our Enemies, and haſt put them to ſhame that hated us. Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but to thy Name be given the glory; for if thou hadſt not been on our ſide, when men roſe up againſt us, they had ſwallowed us up quick.</p>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Thou, O God, waſt pleaſed to do mighty and marvellous things for us, whereof we rejoice, thine Angel encamped round about us whilſt we were in great fear, and hath delivered us. O Lord, more
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:174612:97"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="187" facs="tcp:174612:97"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="188" facs="tcp:174612:98"/> and more encreaſe our Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; maintain ſtill thine own cauſe, keep us from all Plots &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of the wicked: And as thou haſt at this time by a hand unexpected, put <hi>Siſera</hi> to flight, and brought our Foes to an end, ſo deſtroy their Armies evermore, and diſperſe their Forces, that we may know thou art the Lord, whoſe Name is <hi>Jehovah;</hi> to whom be Praiſe, now and for evermore, World without end.</p>
                  <closer>Amen</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:174612:98"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A <hi>Preparatory Prayer againſt wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Thoughts, and vain Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations</hi> Page 7</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for</hi> Sunday 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Morning Prayer for the Worſhip of God</hi> 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer at our Entrance into the Church</hi> 21</item>
               <item>Sunday <hi>Noon; for Perſeverance</hi> 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thanſgiving after Evening Prayer, for the Word preached</hi> 24</item>
               <item>Sunday <hi>Even. for pardon of Sin</hi> 25</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for</hi> Monday 29</item>
               <item>Monday <hi>Morning; for a holy Life</hi> 30</item>
               <item>Monday <hi>Noon; for forgiveneſs of Sins</hi> 33</item>
               <item>Monday <hi>Night; for God's preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for</hi> Tueſday 36</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:174612:99"/>
               <item>Tueſday <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn. for Protection from our Enemies</hi> 39</item>
               <item>Tueſday <hi>Noon; for God's Grace and Favour</hi> 41</item>
               <item>Tueſday <hi>Night; a Thanksgiving for God's Mercies</hi> 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for</hi> Wedneſday 44</item>
               <item>Wedneſday <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn. for Repentance</hi> 47</item>
               <item>Wedneſday <hi>Noon; for God's parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular care of us</hi> 49</item>
               <item>Wedneſday <hi>Night; for deliverance from Sin</hi> 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for</hi> Thurſday 53</item>
               <item>Thurſ. <hi>Morn. a Sacrifice of Praiſe</hi> 55</item>
               <item>Thurſ. <hi>Noon; for God's Bleſſing</hi> 58</item>
               <item>Thurſday <hi>Night; for Deliverance from ſudden Death</hi> 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for</hi> Friday 62</item>
               <item>Friday <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn. a Confeſſion of Sin</hi> 65</item>
               <item>Frid. <hi>Noon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, for God's Direction</hi> 69</item>
               <item>Friday <hi>Night; againſt Carnal Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity</hi> 71</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for</hi> Saturday 75</item>
               <item>Saturd. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn. for God's Providence</hi> 78</item>
               <item>Saturd. <hi>Noon; for Tranquillity of Spirit</hi> 81</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:174612:99"/>
               <item>Sat. <hi>Night; for Remiſſion of Sins</hi> 84</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A confeſſion of Sins before the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 87</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer before the Sacrament</hi> 94</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thankſg. after the Sacrament</hi> 95</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Morn. Prayer for a priv. Perſon</hi> 98</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Even. Prayer for a priv. Perſon</hi> 101</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Morn. Prayer for a priv. Family</hi> 104</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Even Prayer for a priv. Family</hi> 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations for the Sick</hi> 115</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer in time of Sickneſs</hi> 117</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Pray. by thoſe that viſit the Sick</hi> 123</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meditations after Recovery</hi> 126</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thankſgiving after Recovery</hi> 128</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer fit to be ſaid at any time</hi> 131</item>
               <item>Prayers for all Perſons and Occaſions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for the Church</hi> 134</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for the King,</hi> &amp;c. 136</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for the Royal Family</hi> 137</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for our Parents</hi> 138</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer of Parents for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> 140</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for our Friends,</hi> &amp;c. 141</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer of a Wife for her Husb.</hi> 142</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer of a Husb. for his Wife</hi> 143</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:174612:100"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer of an Orphan</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Widow's Prayer</hi> 145</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Servant's Prayer</hi> 146</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Maid's Prayer</hi> 149</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer when afflicted in Mind</hi> 149</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thankſg. for our Redemption</hi> 152</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer of a Woman with Child</hi> 154</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Midwife's Prayer</hi> 157</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer by thoſe that are preſent with a Woman in Travail</hi> 159</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A thanksgiving by thoſe that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent after Delivery</hi> 162</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A thankſgiving by the Woman after her Delivery</hi> 164</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thanksg. after any Calamity</hi> 166</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer before taking of Phyſick</hi> 169</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer before a Journey,</hi> &amp;c. 173</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer upon return from a Journey or Voya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> 175</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Mariner's Prayer</hi> 176</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thanksgiving after a Storm</hi> 178</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for Rain</hi> 180</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for fair Weather</hi> 182</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer of a Child,</hi> &amp;c. 184</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer in time of War</hi> 185</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thankſgiving after Victory</hi> 187</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The End of the Table<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174612:100"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
